<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-10-06T20:59:17+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/feed.xml</id><title type="html">agile people management</title><subtitle>A miscellany of real stories, ideas and thoughts about people management, project management and their interconnection in the fields of corporate human resources, digitalization, organizational and change management</subtitle><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">An inability to reach an agreement: is it always a conflict?</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Abilene-paradox/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An inability to reach an agreement: is it always a conflict?" /><published>2023-10-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Abilene-paradox</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Abilene-paradox/">&lt;p&gt;Conflicts are part of any organization. Some of them have a destructive nature that ruins a productive working climate. Others are essential elements to synchronize different points of view during problem-solving that drive a team towards common targets. Usually several parties are involved in a conflict and it has a real cause or a set of causes that lie in various clusters: scarce resources, cost, priorities, processes, personal work styles, lack of competencies, missing or inappropriate ground rules, personality issues, etc. Ignoring or postponing conflict resolution with a real cause might lead to frustration, anger, and blooming faultfinding behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming behavior is a solid unhealthy symptom of a company and, often by default, it is assigned to the inability to manage conflict. However, it might result from the so-called &lt;strong&gt;Abilene paradox&lt;/strong&gt;, when there is no real conflict cause and involved people concur on the actions they want to take and then together do the opposite. Jerry B. Harvey says: &lt;em&gt;“Organizations frequently take actions in contradiction to what they really want to do and therefore defeat the very purposes they are trying to achieve.”&lt;/em&gt; It sounds absurd to some extent, but it happens more often than one could think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, I was a business partner of one industrial division that operated in a highly competitive market and had very demanding big clients. One day, a country account manager brought great news — the biggest local client wanted to replace its current automation system with the most modern and advanced one. The required technology was already piloting in the company in another country but on the local market, neither this division nor their competitors had ever undertaken such a project before. At the same time, this 7-figures project was considered a profitable one, and it also was seen as a door opener for a new market niche in the country. The division’s headquarters has agreed to support the local team. The country CEO was excited and pushy about this project because its implementation could advance the businesses of other divisions with this customer. The country division lead has already visualized how this project would strategically change the opportunity block for his business. The head of engineering looked forward to the acceleration of building up-to-date technical competencies and massive knowledge transfer to his department. The commercial division lead was satisfied with the planned project margin and checked that major risks had been considered. The project lead was motivated to take on this career-boosting challenge and actively participated in preparation for the tender. After a tough fight with competitors during the tender, the division won the project. The project plan was updated, monitoring systems were set, and the exciting journey began. After one year of execution, the project status became red. At the end of the second year, the company was fighting to reduce penalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the lessons learned session, it was discovered that key decision-makers who could influence the ‘no-go’ decision and stop this project did not share and properly articulate their concerns with others. The head of engineering discovered that the headquarters’ technical department had used a lot of contractors and subcontractors for the pilot and, in fact, had limited relevant in-house knowledge. So, knowledge acquisition became more complicated. He reported it as one of the risks but did not set the red flag for the project to start, because he saw how excited the rest were about the project. The division lead had a bad feeling about the project because the client was known as fault-finding and often changing an agreed work scope. However, he did not want his weird experience to damage opportunities, and believed in the professional mastery of the project manager and head of engineering, who seemed not to have strong doubts about the project’s success. Besides that, he could not report to the country CEO or HQ management gut feelings instead of confirmed facts. The commercial division lead was surprised that some risks were evaluated lower than she would expect, but as they were all from the technical side, she relied on estimates and mitigation actions suggested by the responsible colleagues. The project manager knew that the project would be complicated from technical and organizational points of view, with a real chance of failing because of diverse factors. He also saw an enormous inspiration about the project and support from all sides. So, he decided to do his best to be a good team player and focused on avoiding mistakes in project management processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the described situation, there was no real conflict cause, directly the opposite: all decision-makers wanted to support each other and to achieve the same target. On the individual level, each of them recognized a problem and knew how to cope with it. However, their inaccurate communication led to a misperception of the collective reality. This point was the fork in the road where the team went off the desired path and headed to Abilene. Then, with invalid information, members took collective decisions that started actions contrary to what they wanted to do, and arrived at the opposite results: instead of new lucrative business opportunities there were losses of money and to some extent competitive advantages and reputation. The paradoxical nature of this issue is &lt;strong&gt;the inability to manage agreement&lt;/strong&gt;: on the surface, it looks like team members have aligned their interests and agreed on actions to achieve a common target. But inside, their decision-making was based on misrepresented data and actually the team was far away from an agreement that its members indeed wanted to have.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/Abilene-paradox.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;120%&quot; style=&quot;float:center&quot; /&gt;
For a small or mid-sized company, such an Abilene trip can turn out to be the final destination of its business. For a big company with a stronger margin of business safety and bigger resources the situation might develop further and according to Harvey affects working productivity and well-being: &lt;em&gt;“As a result of taking actions that are counterproductive, organization members experience frustration, anger, irritation, and dissatisfaction with their organization. Frequently, they also blame authority figures and one another.”&lt;/em&gt; If the paradox is not recognized and appropriate corrective actions are not taken, most probably it ends in Abilene and then will repeat itself with greater intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of reasons why team members are not able to manage an agreement. One of them is the fear of being tabbed as a “non-team player”. The dominant trend in organizational development focusing strongly on teamwork and positive thinking besides the obviously positive side that ensures the development of breakthrough technologies and businesses might serve as a greenhouse of an individual’s fear of being one who spoils a team’s common inspiration and excitement. Another reason is deeply rooted in the dimension of corporate culture, when disagreement could be considered as ‘disloyalty’ and no one wants to be a messenger that brings bad news. The list of grounds can be extended to various aspects of psychology, human perceptions, individual values, motivation, and group dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paradox can be revealed on the way or post factum. Anyway, a search for the culprits is not the right action to take. It is counterproductive and diverts a team from problem-solving required to redirect a company along the route it really wants to take. Attempts to eliminate the paradox by applying standard methods of conflict resolution are doomed to fail, because any Abilene trip is the inability to manage agreement, not the inability to manage a conflict. The power to destroy the paradox comes from speaking to the underlying reality of the situation. Therefore, accurate messaging and a corporate culture that favors fearless and open communication are the keys to being able to manage agreements really beneficial for a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/inability-reach-agreement-always-conflict-svetlana-ilina%3FtrackingId=FbqTnKq37JURbGb2yI9NYQ%253D%253D/?trackingId=FbqTnKq37JURbGb2yI9NYQ%3D%3D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="case-study" /><category term="communication" /><category term="conflict" /><category term="culture" /><category term="fallacy" /><category term="paradox" /><category term="team" /><summary type="html">Conflicts are part of any organization. Some of them have a destructive nature that ruins a productive working climate. Others are essential elements to synchronize different points of view during problem-solving that drive a team towards common targets. Usually several parties are involved in a conflict and it has a real cause or a set of causes that lie in various clusters: scarce resources, cost, priorities, processes, personal work styles, lack of competencies, missing or inappropriate ground rules, personality issues, etc. Ignoring or postponing conflict resolution with a real cause might lead to frustration, anger, and blooming faultfinding behavior.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">22 Common Errors in Reasoning</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/logical-fallacies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="22 Common Errors in Reasoning" /><published>2023-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/logical-fallacies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/logical-fallacies/">&lt;p&gt;Efficient communication is a cornerstone of any successful project, and arguments and debates are an important part of it. Each good communication should have a call to action. In order to achieve it, the affected groups of people must experience all the stages of the commitment curve: preparation (contact, awareness), acceptance (understanding, positive perception), and commitment.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/Conner-commitment-curve.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
Logic is a powerful tool for persuading an audience by providing valid argumentation and reasonable statements in the course of the communication process. However, not every argument or statement is solid. Some might have errors in reasoning and rhetoric and lead to incorrect conclusions. These are so-called “logical fallacies”. They indicate either illegitimate arguments or irrelevant points, and often can be identified because they lack evidence that supports their statement. They can be used intentionally to manipulate or trick an audience or can be made unwittingly by mistake. Fallacies have a lot of variations and may be present in all forms of human communication. Often they are classified by errors in the structure (a formal fallacy), and errors in the form, content, or context of the argument (an informal fallacy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;does-not-follow-non-sequitur&quot;&gt;“Does not follow” &lt;em&gt;(non sequitur)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All &lt;strong&gt;formal fallacies&lt;/strong&gt; are associated with &lt;em&gt;non sequitur&lt;/em&gt; error types where reasoning goes wrong, i.e. a presented conclusion is not necessarily a logical result of the given facts. Reaching logical conclusions depends on the proper analysis of statements taken to be true and used as a basis for reasoning, so-called premises. In order to work, logic requires decisive statements based on reliable and complete facts accepted by the audience. It also leans on which factors are recognized and ignored by the premises. Therefore, premises that are correct but ignore other essential information might drive misleading conclusions.
Some examples of formal fallacies are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In 2020 the average market salary of IT specialists has noticeably increased, therefore the qualification of IT staff hired in that year must be very high.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Developers wear comfortable hoodies and jeans. Peter comes to the first interview in a business suit, therefore he is not a developer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some high performers have the potential for further development and belong to a company’s top talent group. After a performance review, Marie was evaluated as a high performer, therefore, she is a top talent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The landscape of &lt;strong&gt;informal fallacies&lt;/strong&gt; has a vast variety and can be categorized in different ways. Among others, it might be a lack of relevance, present improper presumptions, faulty generalizations, and errors in assigning causation. Some of these fallacies are known since the first public speeches in Ancient times, others have appeared and bloomed together with the development of advertising, marketing, political technologies, social media, and the business environment. Sitting in a business meeting, surfing the Internet, or going to a shopping mall, we can observe plenty of logically unsound premises and based on them false conclusions, like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;appeal-to-authority-argumentum-ad-auctoritate&quot;&gt;Appeal to authority &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad auctoritate)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a misusage of an authority’s opinion. A statement made by an authority on some topic is used as evidence to support one’s argument disregarding circumstances such as the reliability and relevance of the information to the issue, the existence of a widespread agreement among authorities, or alternative opinions on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;To be competitive, our company has to speed up the implementation of modern technologies and agile approaches. Jeff Sutherland states that the SCRUM framework can be used in any business, therefore we must apply this method to all our construction projects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;appeal-to-emotions&quot;&gt;Appeal to emotions&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a set of fallacies provoking emotions (fear, flattery, pity, ridicule, etc.) to win a statement or a debate. These fallacies attempt to pull on an audience’s emotions, manipulate, and distract listeners instead of using valid reasoning to obtain an agreement. For instance, the &lt;strong&gt;appeal to pity&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad misericordiam)&lt;/em&gt; aims to generate feelings of sympathy or mercy, or the &lt;strong&gt;appeal to ridicule&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(reductio ad ridiculum, ad absurdum)&lt;/em&gt; is a diversion from the merits of the opponent’s arguments by mocking or stating that an opponent’s position is laughable or absurd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;During annual performance reviews, such a speech of a line manager excusing the underperformance of an employee is not a rare case: “Lora is a nice young lady. This year was very difficult for her: she lost her grandmother and has permanent problems with her boyfriend. That is why she is sometimes rude to clients, quarrels with colleagues, and has missed several important deadlines. If we assign her to the ‘need improvements’ category, it will be an additional stress for her.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;appeal-to-hypocrisy-you-too-tu-quoque&quot;&gt;Appeal to hypocrisy/ “you too” &lt;em&gt;(tu quoque)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fallacy deflects criticism away from oneself by accusing the other person of the same problem or something comparable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are not in a position to criticize the retention methods of my department while the fluctuation rate of your department is also higher than the targeted one.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;appeal-to-ignorance-argumentum-ad-ignorantiam&quot;&gt;Appeal to ignorance &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad ignorantiam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is based on the speculation that a proposition must be true because it has not been proven false or vice versa. The fallacy allows shifting the need for proof of a statement away from the person making a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;We have no evidence that this risk has ever been realized in our projects, so it has to be excluded from risk analysis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bandwagon-appeal-argument-to-people-argumentum-ad-populum&quot;&gt;Bandwagon appeal/ Argument to people &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad populum)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It assumes that something is true or right because others think it is so. The fallacy is an attempt to influence one to think the same way as the multitude (most people or a group of people) does. It appeals to emotions and the feeling of togetherness rather than facts and evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A genuine patriot of our company always goes the extra mile and never complains about overtime.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;begging-the-question-petitio-principii&quot;&gt;Begging the Question &lt;em&gt;(petitio principii)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A statement that should be validated is presented as truth and misled to assume something has been proved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overwhelmed and ineffective modernization should be stopped.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;circular-reasoning-circulus-in-probando&quot;&gt;Circular reasoning &lt;em&gt;(circulus in probando)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a restatement of the same argument rather than actually proving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our manager is an excellent communicator because he speaks effectively.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;changing-the-subject-red-herring&quot;&gt;Changing the subject/ Red herring&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the common tactics that diverts attention from the main issue by introducing irrelevant points intended to replace the lack of real arguments or to replace implicitly the subject of the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our team lead wants to talk about my morning lateness, so I asked her what she is going to do with delays in customers’ payments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;cherry-picking-card-stacking-fallacy-of-incomplete-evidence&quot;&gt;Cherry-picking/ Card-stacking/ Fallacy of incomplete evidence&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens by carefully selecting facts and evidences to confirm a particular position and skipping or ignoring data that may contradict this position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Presentation of achievements:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-06-12-card-stacking.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;genetic-fallacy-fallacy-of-origins-fallacy-of-virtue&quot;&gt;Genetic fallacy/ Fallacy of origins/ Fallacy of virtue&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fallacy assumes that information or arguments are validated based on their source of origin (a person, group, organizational unit, or institute) rather than their content. The focus shifts from ‘what’ and ‘why’ have been said to ‘who’ said it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The objections to the new target-setting process come only from the R&amp;amp;D department and can be ignored.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;false-cause-post-hoc-ergo-propter-hoc&quot;&gt;False cause &lt;em&gt;(post hoc ergo propter hoc)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens when a conclusion is solely based on the order of events and other factors potentially responsible for the outcome are not considered. In other words, a temporal sequence implies causation: if ‘A’ occurred after ‘B’, then ‘B’ must have caused ‘A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;We should not arrange an open-air company party because every time we do, heavy rain comes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;false-comparison-faulty-analogy-comparing-apples-and-oranges&quot;&gt;False comparison/ Faulty analogy/ &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Comparing apples and oranges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It assumes that if two things are similar in one or several aspects, they are necessarily identical in some others or all the rest facets. Often, a similarity might be based on ignorance of additional factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;This product development project has the same estimated duration as one of our infrastructure projects, therefore it requires a similar budget.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;false-compromise-argument-to-moderation-middle-ground-fallacy-of-the-golden-mean-argumentum-ad-temperantiam&quot;&gt;False compromise/ Argument to moderation/ Middle ground/ Fallacy of the golden mean &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad temperantiam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It assumes that a compromise between two opposite positions is always correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subject matter experts estimate a project duration of one year, but the customer wants its completion in 4 months, therefore a sales manager has prepared a contract with an 8-month project duration without corrections in the project scope, output, and budget.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;false-dilemma-false-dichotomy-either--or-black-or-white&quot;&gt;False dilemma/ False dichotomy/ Either – or/ Black or white&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fallacy reduces the options of a complex issue to two extremes: often one right, one wrong. This is a manipulative tool aimed to promote one side and exaggerate the negative effects of another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Internship students come to a company to work hard or to loaf.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A company has either to invest in A, B, and C technologies to become the market leader or sell its business.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;hasty-generalization-fallacy-of-insufficient-sample&quot;&gt;Hasty generalization/ Fallacy of insufficient sample&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens when reasoning is based on insufficient or biased evidence. Often, this fallacy can be met in presentations of survey results when conclusions are derived from a small sample group that does not sufficiently represent an entire population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Despite good grades during his study, the intern does a lot of mistakes in working tasks. Therefore, our department won’t accept interns who graduated from this university anymore.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-08-12-pulse-response-rate.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The results of &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/pulse-check/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the pulse-check 202X&lt;/a&gt; show that in our company employees are very satisfied with their line managers. The average satisfaction value is 76,75.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;irrelevant-conclusion-missing-the-point-ignoratio-elenchi&quot;&gt;Irrelevant conclusion/ Missing the point &lt;em&gt;(ignoratio elenchi)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens when provided arguments may be valid, but do not address or relate to the issue in the discussed question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;John is clearly an experienced manager. He has a warm family life and regularly takes part in volunteer projects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;personal-attack-ad-hominem&quot;&gt;Personal attack &lt;em&gt;(ad hominem)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an attack on the character of a person rather than a debate about her opinions or arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is a waste of time to discuss the claims of the procurement department about the project organization because they are all foolish quibblers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;slippery-slope&quot;&gt;Slippery slope&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It supposes that if a certain event occurs, it will necessarily lead to a chain of small steps or future events ending in a predefined result. The starting point is equated to the outcome. In other words, if we do not want this result to occur, the initial event must be prevented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;If psychometrics is not used in an assessment center (AC), AC results will not be valid.&lt;/em&gt; 
(Psychometrics is reliable and suitable for some situations instrument. However, the design of an assessment center is a complex task with multiple facets that affected its validity.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;straw-man&quot;&gt;Straw Man&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an oversimplification of an opponent’s viewpoint and then attacks a different subject rather than the topic being discussed. The purpose of this misdirection is to make one’s position look stronger than it actually is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Division leads who don’t support a continuous increase of the company’s well-being budget hate our employees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;sunk-cost&quot;&gt;Sunk cost&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fallacy describes the tendency to follow through on an endeavor if time, effort, or money have been already invested into it, regardless of whether the additional costs outweigh the potential benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;We have invested $ xxx into a HRM system, but it does not fit our internal processes and the results of its implementation are far away from the planned ones. The system provider offers customization, it will cost in the range of the initial investment or slightly more. Considering already spent money, time, and effort, it makes sense to customize the system.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;testimonial-anecdotal-evidence&quot;&gt;Testimonial/ Anecdotal evidence&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens when a statement is made only based on personal observation, collected in a casual manner. Intentionally this fallacy is used in advertising when a respected or well-known person promotes something in an area where they lack expert knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A famous artist recommends a bank.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The chief accountant recommends to the chief engineer how to set up a production line.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Spotting weak points in arguments is a gained habit. It can and should be trained to be applied in communication activities. It is helpful to notice mistakes in reasoning being in a receiver position to separate the grain from the chaff. And it is even more important to check your own messages on fallacies to avoid transmitting misleading information. Logical reasoning is one of the most powerful convincing methods, however, to strengthen communication efficiency it is worth addressing the values and emotions of people besides arguments. Therefore, experienced influencers are using a diverse spectrum of instruments and methods to work with and persuade their audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/22-common-errors-reasoning-svetlana-ilina/?trackingId=oYspSlnyTtydt6C1YM1oDw%3D%3D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="communication" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="logic" /><category term="fallacy" /><category term="pitfall" /><summary type="html">Efficient communication is a cornerstone of any successful project, and arguments and debates are an important part of it. Each good communication should have a call to action. In order to achieve it, the affected groups of people must experience all the stages of the commitment curve: preparation (contact, awareness), acceptance (understanding, positive perception), and commitment. Logic is a powerful tool for persuading an audience by providing valid argumentation and reasonable statements in the course of the communication process. However, not every argument or statement is solid. Some might have errors in reasoning and rhetoric and lead to incorrect conclusions. These are so-called “logical fallacies”. They indicate either illegitimate arguments or irrelevant points, and often can be identified because they lack evidence that supports their statement. They can be used intentionally to manipulate or trick an audience or can be made unwittingly by mistake. Fallacies have a lot of variations and may be present in all forms of human communication. Often they are classified by errors in the structure (a formal fallacy), and errors in the form, content, or context of the argument (an informal fallacy).</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Critical Issues and Success Factors in HR projects: Processes</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Processes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Critical Issues and Success Factors in HR projects: Processes" /><published>2023-04-21T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Processes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Processes/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“If you can’t fly, then run. If you can’t run, then walk. If you can’t walk, then crawl. But whatever you do, you have to keep moving forward.”&lt;/em&gt;  Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within recent decades business environment has been described as &lt;em&gt;volatile, uncertain, complex, and ambiguous&lt;/em&gt; (VUCA), and companies had to shape their strategies and elaborate approaches to navigate through frequent, rapid, and sometimes confusing trends and changes in technology, social, and business culture. Drastic economical, political, technological, social, and climate challenges of the last years sharpen the chaotic component of the world and push businesses to deal with a &lt;em&gt;brittle, anxious, nonlinear, and incomprehensible&lt;/em&gt; (BANI) environment. It dictates and drives immediate business responses to catch new opportunities and adjust a company’s strategy and objectives to secure its vitality. These changes speed up HR transformation and require HR-function to become more analytical, more agile, more digital, and more competent in handling different programs and initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, transformative HR initiatives and programs comprise diverse &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/PM-HR_strangers-or-buddies/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HR projects&lt;/a&gt; endeavoring to support the achievements of specific business objectives, to deliver value-add, and to reorganize, automate, and improve processes. As with any project, they are time-boxed and aimed at delivering results. Despite significant diversity in purpose, &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complexity&lt;/a&gt;, duration, available resources, budget, risks, and other constraints, there are some &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Hindrances-in-HRprojects/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;common critical issues&lt;/a&gt; to keep an eye on in any HR project. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/critical-issues-hr-projects.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
Handling these fulcrums — &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholders&lt;/a&gt;, processes, culture, and competencies — directly redound in project success or failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processes belong to and ensure the core functionalities of HR. Process management in the context of HR projects has several aspects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the interconnection of processes across different HR areas, compound to a common system, and leverage points;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the conjunction of HR processes with a business process system;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;processes and approaches to drive and handle HR initiatives, programs, and projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interconnection-of-hr-processes-and-leverage-points&quot;&gt;Interconnection of HR processes and leverage points&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HR is made up of complex, intertwined processes and systems, which are highly integrated into and influenced by a company’s culture, strategy, and operational business objectives. Often &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Maturity-of-processes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the maturity of HR processes&lt;/a&gt; reflects the attitude and approaches to the organization of processes in a company or trails a step behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HR projects touch and in most cases directly concentrate on processes. An HR process is a collection of tasks, steps, or activities that are performed, usually in a specific order, and result in a provision of services. Multiple processes in different HR areas are interwoven, often organized in systems, and work together to achieve the same goal or goals. To get a reliable system processes should be as simple as possible, consistent, and documented. There is no need for long eloquent process descriptions, but a process map is very helpful to monitor duplications, missing and “grey” zones, and leverage points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An effective working system has good vitality in tolerating accidental errors and manageable interventions. At the same time, any system has critical places where intentional actions can create a ripple effect that leads to lasting positive or negative change. Identifying such leverage points is a tricky task. It should be done by subject matter experts, who are familiar with the system’s features and understand how changes might impact inputs and outcomes of processes on a granular level. Because of the complexity and interconnectedness of HR processes, intentional, but crude or low-controlled interventions damage their stability and efficiency, which has an outsized impact on the functioning of the system as a whole. To avoid it, a regular audit of processes should be done to ensure system sustainability, adaptability, and efforts- and cost-effectiveness of the existing processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, an HR project started as a response to a strategic business initiative serves as a great impetus to the revision of HR processes and systems. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2021/2021-06-23.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
For example, an HR project aimed at supporting rapid business growth won’t be limited to one HR area and its processes, even if at the beginning only recruitment targets are set. After a kick-off meeting, it will be clear that the targets’ accomplishment requires a lot of supportive actions and sub-projects in adjacent areas. One of &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/PM-and-HRtransformation/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;my headcount ramp-up projects&lt;/a&gt; ended up in the revision of the whole HR system, designing new and adjusting some existing processes in different HR areas, establishing a lot of conjunctions with business processes, and influencing on development of the corporate culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conjunction-with-a-business-process-system&quot;&gt;Conjunction with a business process system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An assessment of the influence of changes on internal HR processes and systems is to be an initial step in any HR project. It has to be done proactively and cover the complete range of processes in the directly affected and coterminous zones. Besides that, adjoining processes in other functional areas should also be considered. For example, those who survived an ERP migration most probably can recall a lot of complaints from a controlling department about strange data appearing in their reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In immature companies, a generally chaotic organization of processes often disguises the real impact of HR processes on other functions and their business processes, which might lead to an underestimation of their interconnectivity and sway on business results. On the contrary, in companies with a mature organization of processes, the system might be extremely complicated and bureaucratic to allow all-around assessments. In both cases, HR professionals have to deal with comprehensive and go-ahead estimations of internal HR and cross-functional interdependencies to prevent an increasing number of blocking stakeholders, growing project complexity, and deteriorating the quality of a project outcome. Unfortunately, such estimations are not always a strong suit in HR projects, which leads to a permanent search for workaround solutions to close emerging gaps. That spawns low-controlled overlapping and duplications of processes, fosters excrescent deleterious “a process for a process”-elements, and damages a system’s integrity, consistency, transparency, and stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;handling-hr-initiatives-programs-and-projects&quot;&gt;Handling HR initiatives, programs, and projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drastic changes in reaction speed and agility of HR-function to meet requirements of business transformation result in a focus on project work. However, the principles of project management are underestimated or, to some extent, ignored in HR world. That might cause compelled rework, overrun budget and time, or overall outcome failure. As with any project, HR initiative or program should follow the common &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Five-steps/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;process of project management&lt;/a&gt; and, if necessary, tune its phases to corporate, legal, and regional requirements. A typical process of managing HR projects usually sequences two core stages embracing important phases.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-04-21-phases-hr-projects.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;170%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial project stage is &lt;em&gt;a compass&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. it sets a general project direction and its frames. It starts with clarification and &lt;strong&gt;analysis of needs&lt;/strong&gt;. During this phase, plausible ideas are collected, analyzed, and clarified with a project sponsor. A vision of the outcome, requirements, and involved parties are typical results of this phase. It is followed by &lt;strong&gt;high-level estimates&lt;/strong&gt; of benefits, risks, complexity, amount of work, costs, resources, and schedule. Depending on project specifics, other constraints can be also assessed. This phase is a basis for preparing decisions about the project realization, refining the list of requirements, allocation of resources, and budget assignment. Skipping any of the basic estimates or the whole phase guarantees a bulk of unpleasant surprises during the project execution. The &lt;strong&gt;approval&lt;/strong&gt; phase completes the initial stage. During this process step, decisions about the project execution are taken, targets and acceptance criteria are set, and budget, time, and key resources are confirmed. A frivolous attitude to the importance of the initial stage puts in pledge enormous pressure on a project team during the execution stage and jeopardizes the success of a not yet-started project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;clarification&lt;/strong&gt; commences the execution stage and focuses on project objectives, scope, prioritization of tasks, stakeholders, available resources (people, time, money), risks, and constraints. Best practices assume that an appointed project manager arranges a project kick-off meeting to discuss these issues and agrees upon the project organization and execution with a sponsor, subject matter experts, a project team, and key decision makers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the &lt;strong&gt;planning&lt;/strong&gt; phase, a project plan including technical and functional specifications, risks analysis, time and cost forecasts, work breakdown structure, time schedule with milestones, and a communication strategy should be developed. An excessively detailed and rigid plan as well as the opposite—an extremely sketchy plan does not provide the required guidance and support during the implementation. The detailing should be suitable to make founded decisions and see trees without losing the picture of the entire forest. The results of clarification and planning phases serve as &lt;em&gt;a map&lt;/em&gt; with drafted trails through the project to achieve its targets and objectives. Starting an implementation journey, it is vital to have both a compass and a map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the common mistakes in handling HR projects is a lack of searching for optimal leverage points in HR processes and systems or postponing it from the planning to the implementation phase. Another critical issue that should be taken into account during the planning phase is solving the dilemmas: keeping a functional simplicity vs. ignorance of a bounded complexity and moving beyond an acceptable level of complexity vs. unreasonable simplification. The thoughtful planning provides a comprehensive overview of the project landscape and allows rational navigation between alternatives, mitigation of potential risks, optimal allocation of resources, and overall uncertainty reduction that increase the chances of successful project completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;implementation&lt;/strong&gt; is the most visible, dynamic, and time-consuming project phase. Rollout under permanent monitoring, controlling, and supervision of work progress are the principal components of this phase. At the same time, it highlights defects in handling HR projects done in the previous process steps. Some of them can be patched with a slight variation of the project outcome. Others might lead to the growing &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Onion-syndrome/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;onion syndrome in a project&lt;/a&gt;, a sizable run-over budget, a significant increase in time, or project failure. Having a compass and a well-done map allows a project team confidently to solve and maneuver between the different pop-up problems during the implementation and overcome emerging challenges of the BANI environment. In the pursuit of agility, one of the frequent pitfalls during this phase is the launching of many simultaneous changes in various HR processes and systems without their proper piloting or at least revisiting the planning phase. That often creates chaos in a project and complicates its handling and the achievement of the set targets and objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The execution stage is completed by obtaining acceptance of project results, archiving project documentation, releasing project resources and infrastructure, and analyzing the achieved outcome. Retrospectives are the most important component of the &lt;strong&gt;closure&lt;/strong&gt; phase that focuses on lessons learned and room for improvements in processes, organization, and handling of HR projects. That elaborates a valuable basis for the successful realization of further HR initiatives and programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prosperous launch of transformative HR programs is a challenging task that requires a deep understanding of process management and expert subject knowledge. Despite the functional specifics, any HR initiative is just one of the possible types of projects to which standard project management methodology and approaches should be applied. It helps to avoid a lot of traps in handling HR projects, prevents realization derailment, and accelerates the transition of the HR function to the new partnering level with the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Josh Bersin Company. HR Predictions for 2023. www.joshbersin.com&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jeff Sutherland (2014). SCRUM: The Art of Doing Twice the Work in Half the Time. ISBN: 9781847941107&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tom DeMarco (2002). Slack: getting past burnout, busywork, and the myth of total efficiency. ISBN: 0-7679-0769-8&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donella H. Meadows (1999). Leverage Points: Places to Intervene in a System. The Sustainability Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jamais Cascio (2020). Facing the Age of Chaos. www.medium.com&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Project Management Institute (2017, 2021). 
&lt;em&gt;A Guide to the Project Management Body of Knowledge (PMBOK® Guide).&lt;/em&gt; Sixth and Seventh Editions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Axelos. (2017). 
&lt;em&gt;Managing Successful Projects with PRINCE2®.&lt;/em&gt; Sixth Edition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://svetlana-ilina.medium.com/critical-issues-and-success-factors-in-hr-projects-processes-65302332368f&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="BANI" /><category term="VUCA" /><category term="hr-project" /><category term="processes" /><category term="risk" /><category term="success-factor" /><category term="project-management" /><category term="pitfall" /><category term="initiation" /><category term="execution" /><summary type="html">“If you can’t fly, then run. If you can’t run, then walk. If you can’t walk, then crawl. But whatever you do, you have to keep moving forward.” Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Transformation of HR Processes:from chaos to ecosystem</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Maturity-of-processes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transformation of HR Processes:from chaos to ecosystem" /><published>2023-02-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-02-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Maturity-of-processes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Maturity-of-processes/">&lt;p&gt;According to Wikipedia, a process &lt;em&gt;“is a series or set of activities that interact to produce a result; it may occur once-only or be recurrent or periodic“&lt;/em&gt;. These activities are to be decomposed into some number of steps, sequenced in a specific order, and performed for a purpose. In a business, multiple processes work together to achieve a company’s goals. Processes are the carcass of any complex organization. They serve to reduce chaos  and provide systematic approaches, methods, practices, and procedures to deal with both repetitive and unique tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Process maturity is the extent to which a specific process is explicitly defined, managed, measured, controlled, and effective. One of the most commonly used process maturity frameworks derives from the software development area, where the quality of processes has an immediately visible effect on business results. It is a part of the Capability Maturity Model for Software (CMM). The framework comprises five levels:
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/5steps-processes-maturity.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Initial&lt;/em&gt;: The process is characterized as ad hoc, and occasionally even chaotic. Few processes are defined, and success depends on individual efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Repeatable&lt;/em&gt;: Basic processes are established. Some processes are repeatable, possibly with consistent results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defined&lt;/em&gt;: There are sets of defined and documented standard processes established and subject to some degree of improvement over time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Managed&lt;/em&gt;: Detailed measures of the process and outcome quality are collected and controlled.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Optimizing&lt;/em&gt;: Continuous process improvement is enabled by quantitative feedback from the process and from piloting innovative ideas and technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maturity of processes’ organization indicates both the richness of a company’s processes and the consistency with which it is applied in an enterprise. At a given time, different processes can be assigned to diverse maturity levels that affect the overall level of an organization of processes. With an immature organization, most processes are improvised by practitioners and even specified ones are not rigorously followed or enforced. With a mature organization, processes are accurately communicated to executors and other &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholders&lt;/a&gt;, work activities are carried out according to the planned processes, and the quality of outcome and customer satisfaction is monitored, controlled, and continuously improved. The more mature an organization of processes is better an objective, quantitative basis for judging quality and analyzing problems with outcomes and processes themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting from some degree of organizational development, processes tend to be integrated, interconnected, and organized into a common system. As a company matures, its processes become better defined within and across different business areas and more consistently implemented throughout the organization. HR is made up of complex, intertwined processes and systems, which are highly integrated into and influenced by a company’s culture, strategy, and operational business objectives. Often the maturity of HR processes reflects the attitude and the way the organization of processes in a company or trails a little bit behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reinvent-the-wheel&quot;&gt;Reinvent the wheel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the starting stage where any task is titled as a strategic challenge requiring an elaboration of a unique solution. This is a typical situation for startups and unfortunately not a rare case for mid-sized companies. The key characteristics of the HR function at this stage are a lack of systematic approach, chaotic organization of work, unpredictable outcomes for similar tasks, and high dependence of results on individual efforts. These might foster a forming of counterproductive working habits, which hamper the movement to the next organizational level and a significant resistance of executors to changes. The immature HR organization is reactionary, and practitioners are usually focused on solving immediate crises. A prolonged jamming at this stage prevents HR from being considered a reliable partner and a value-add for the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first transformative step from the chaos is to identify &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/PMandTasks/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;administrative, operational, tactical, and strategic HR tasks&lt;/a&gt; and classify them in terms of repetitiveness, for example, frequent, rare, and unique. In an immature organization, a portfolio of HR services is very limited and most probably bounded by the basics of administrative and operational tasks. For frequent administrative and operational working tasks, appropriate processes and clear procedures should be designed. A high task recurrence allows practitioners to test and quickly tune processes to be effective. Because of the relative simplicity of tasks, these processes are to be simple, transparent, with clear input and output data, and well-defined and documented sets of required sequential steps. To maximize the effect, these processes are to be coherent to arrange them into simple working systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the essential hindrances at this stage is the capability of HR practitioners, who dealt with truncated HR processes only, to design appropriate consistent processes for different HR areas. A shortcut solution in this situation can be the adoption of processes embedded into one of HRTech solutions offered by software providers. Another option is to invite an external consultant or a process manager from a business to help HR practitioners set up steady and scalable processes. Besides the capability of processes’ design and implementation, supportive change management activities have to be undertaken to ensure smooth and efficient transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;replicate-results&quot;&gt;Replicate results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the next stage of the organization of HR processes on the maturity journey. The main characteristics of the HR function at this level are defined processes for most repetitive tasks, minor deviation of results for similar activities, low dependence on specifics of executors, a set of independent systems and processes with a partial overlapping and the necessity of manual input or Excel-based data exchange between them. Because of the stable delivery of acceptable outcomes for the majority of administrative and operational tasks, HR is a respected function for the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of companies are stuck at this level polishing instead of improving processes and maintaining instead of optimizing a lot of outdated systems. To move forward, HR organization is to focus on bundling independent systems into complex ones to reduce partial duplication of processes and decrease the number of mistakes caused by significant manual data handling. Many processes are to be automated. On the market, there are plenty of HRTech solutions to be selected from and to fit the specific requirements of a company to functionality, set of HR processes, and degree of customization. Such a solution can be embedded into the company’s system of HR processes or the internal organization of HR processes can be adjusted to the solution’s requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-02-28-tasks-levels-frequency.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
Digitalization of HR processes to support the employee lifecycle and a positive employee experience requires significant change management activities to get the acceptance and commitment of all affected stakeholders. To solve such a task, HR practitioners have to know the basics of project management and be capable of applying it in practice. This is another area of improvement. The application of project management to deal with tactical and strategic tasks facilitates HR to become more flexible, proactive, and strategic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;continuous-improvement&quot;&gt;Continuous improvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the advanced stage. The main characteristics of the mature HR function are high automation with the necessary infrastructure to support it, a system of HR processes that ensures managed processes and predictable results for repetitive tasks, a confident handling of unique challenges, a strong focus on the quality of outcome, and integration with some business processes. Roles and responsibilities within the defined processes are clear across the HR and other affected functions. HR organization is a valuable asset for a company and a reliable partner for the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any process is going to have variations. The normal variation within a process is caused by the process itself (for example, typing errors by HR admins). If the output of one process serves as an input for another process, deliberate tracking, control, and management of normal variations open a great reserve for refinements. Continuous process improvement is based on many small, evolutionary steps rather than revolutionary innovations. It should focus on the needs of the HR function in the context of its business environment. Besides cost-effectiveness, agility, and adaptability to business needs, transparency, consistency, predictability, and plainness are core requirements of HR processes and systems. To get better results, efforts should be placed on enhancing the quality of input and output data, optimization of process steps and procedures, shrinking and aligning variations, and tighter integration of HR processes into one common system. The transformative step at this stage is an evolutional move to the HR ecosystem covering all HR-related areas, deeply embedded into a complex business processes system of a company, and embraced by the required project management and culture change activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ecosystem of HR processes is the desired transformative objective. A lot of companies set this transformation as the immediate HR target, ignoring the actual maturity degree of the organization. The ability to implement processes from higher maturity levels does not imply that some levels can be skipped, because each forms a necessary foundation from which to achieve the next stage. HR processes are dedicated to driving job satisfaction, engagement, and productivity of employees, providing a ground for the HR business partnering, shaping the corporate culture, and supporting business in the achieving its strategic goals. In other words, they serve the needs of people and the business. Therefore, the maturity of the organization of HR processes is tightly linked and should be balanced with the maturity level of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/transformation-hr-processes-from-chaos-ecosystem-svetlana-ilina/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="digitalisation" /><category term="hr-transformation" /><category term="processes" /><summary type="html">According to Wikipedia, a process “is a series or set of activities that interact to produce a result; it may occur once-only or be recurrent or periodic“. These activities are to be decomposed into some number of steps, sequenced in a specific order, and performed for a purpose. In a business, multiple processes work together to achieve a company’s goals. Processes are the carcass of any complex organization. They serve to reduce chaos and provide systematic approaches, methods, practices, and procedures to deal with both repetitive and unique tasks.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The “onion syndrome” in projects:7 practical tips to nip it in the bud</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Onion-syndrome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The “onion syndrome” in projects:7 practical tips to nip it in the bud" /><published>2023-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Onion-syndrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Onion-syndrome/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The art of life is a constant readjustment to our surroundings.”&lt;/em&gt;  Okakura Kakuzo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine or recall a case when an additional project pops up in your work. A brief screening shows that probably it won’t be too complicated despite a lot of minor differences from what you have done before. Your working schedule is full of other important or urgent tasks and you simply do not have time for long cogitation and analysis. You ideate how the outcome might look like and know that deviations are natural, unavoidable, and usually they can be fixed during project execution. Raw estimates of the proposed budget and deadlines sound fair, project work looks more or less clear and not scary, ergo you are ready to start your straight path to the project’s success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murphy’s law says: &lt;em&gt;“anything that can go wrong will go wrong”&lt;/em&gt; and suddenly your project illustrates it. In the beginning, there are light signs of potential complications (add-on features or requirements, new stakeholders, another set of deliverables, etc.) that you might not notice or ignore to keep on moving ahead. After some time, you face an issue and might skip or postpone it instead of fixing it. You continue to move forward, ignoring or underestimating consequences. Then another complication pops up and another one, and then some more. Problems are growing like a snowball. The project becomes hardly controlled and its complexity unexpectedly runs to the sky. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/onion-syndrome.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
To patch and fix the appeared troubles, the amount of project work swells, the project duration lengthens, and the project path takes the shape of a bulb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this situation sounds familiar to you, you have already experienced the ‘onion syndrome’, where a bulb size depends on how many problems were piled up and how long necessary corrective actions were postponed. In most cases, there is a good chance to nip it in the bud or minimize its effect by monitoring obvious but critically important aspects of any project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clear-vision&quot;&gt;Clear vision&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first preventive action to diminish an onion’s stature is to have an explicit project goal and its relation to business strategy. Each project is unique and has its features. It lies at the intersection of the three interdependent targets: time, budget, and outcome, and aims to create a certain (in)tangible business value. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-01-31-project-value.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;55%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
As a rule, to start a project regardless of its basic parameters (size, &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complexity&lt;/a&gt;, business area specifics), primary focus (internal or external), and the expected outcome (a product, a service, or a result) it is necessary to have unambiguity among these aspects and a mutual general vision on targets, &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Five-steps/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;processes&lt;/a&gt;, opportunities, and constraints, shared by involved parties. Clarity on the project’s value is a starting point and an ultimate pre-requisite for your successful project journey, which follows by creating a project statement, definition of objectives, and elaboration of a project plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;defined-scope-and-objectives&quot;&gt;Defined scope and objectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fuzzy project objectives can grow a large onion and stimulate a waste of resources and efforts. To avoid it, objectives and project success criteria have to be defined and affirmed. Often project objectives are set based on the S.M.A.R.T. principle, i.e. there are to be specific, measurable, achievable, relevant, and time-bound. They are tightly linked to a project’s scope and influence its filling and defining what is included in the project and what is not. A negligent scope is a good manure for onion, which creates a risk of missing some or all project targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-01-31-project-scope.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A well-defined scope means that it includes all the work required, and only the work required, to complete the project successfully and meet the acceptance criteria. It is measured against the project management plan. The total scope of work to accomplish the project objectives and create the required deliverables is to be hierarchically decomposed into small parts for which cost and duration are estimated and managed. That structuring usually helps to straighten your path to project success and carefully audit the constraints’ landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accounted-constraints&quot;&gt;Accounted constraints&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each company has its own vision, strategy, and business targets that predefined directions of project objectives and outcomes. Internal and external business environments limit the options available to a company during a project, which have to be managed under certain circumstances and constraints. Focusing on results and positive thinking considering no limitations cultivates onion and assassinates the success of a project. Project constraints can be clustered into six categories: time-related, cost or budget-related, quality-related, scope-related, resources-related, and risk-related. Depending on the project, these groups can have different priorities, however, all of them should be accounted for and tracked. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-01-31-project-constraints.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
A change in one constraint often impacts the others. 
The most sensitive to any variation and vital for a project’s success is a triangle: time—cost—quality. Substantial or uncontrolled changes in it might be a sign of the “onion syndrome” in a project. The larger the bulb, the more difficult it is to balance and manage this triple, the other constraints are or will be also strongly affected, and project success becomes hardly achievable. Awareness of possible limitations allows for analyzing, monitoring, and controlling them, and making informed decisions during a project to take the required corrective actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reliable-planning&quot;&gt;Reliable planning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning is a must-have step in any project regardless of its type, selected methodology, and life cycle. It aggregates, clarifies and structures data, sequences, estimates and plans activities to fulfill the prescribed project work. The outcome of the planning step is a project plan, which shapes the desired path to project success and furnishes the basis for tracking and controlling constraints and their deviations. Although usually the initial project plan is modified over time to reflect changes in external and internal environments, it is important to take planning seriously and perform it with accuracy and rational detailing. Reliable project planning reduces uncertainty, anchors the optimal track to project success, makes project work manageable, alarms gaps and contradictions, and provides a solid ground to notice at an early stage an appearance of the “onion syndrome” as well as advantages to shut its effects on the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;committed-stakeholders&quot;&gt;Committed stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the managed project objectives should be &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholder&lt;/a&gt; satisfaction. People, groups, or organizations that could impact or be impacted, or perceive themselves to be affected by the project, are called stakeholders. They are to be identified, analyzed, prioritized and monitored, and the right strategies for their engagement during different project phases have to be developed in order to keep stakeholders satisfied and committed. Often, stakeholder satisfaction is a cornerstone of project success or failure. The key to stakeholder engagement is the focus on continual communication to understand their needs and expectations, in-time address issues, manage conflicting interests, and foster appropriate involvement in decisions and activities. Effective and efficient stakeholder communication ensures that the right message with the right content is delivered to the right person through the right channel at the right time. Once stakeholder satisfaction or commitment is missing, the path of the project can take a bulb, curve, spiral, or another fancy shape, but not the desired straight one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;skilled-and-motivated-team&quot;&gt;Skilled and motivated team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project team belongs to the key stakeholder group with the biggest impact on project success. Therefore, it is vital that a project team possesses the needed competencies and skills to fulfill work and tasks during different project phases and under a project plan to achieve the set targets and objectives. Lack of qualification of executors is one of the common causes of project incompletion, inferior quality of results, or significant increase in budget, time, and efforts spent on the project. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-01-31-skills-motivation-matrix.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
Inaction or implicit faith in the outstanding ability of a project team to settle everything usually makes the situation worse. In order to close skills and competency gaps, requires their identification and then upskilling of team members or hiring the required competence on the market.
Besides skills, another essential aspect is motivation. Only motivated team members can be successfully engaged in a project and will do their best to achieve the desired results in an efficient and thoughtful manner. Once motivation is missing, it immediately affects the team’s commitment and the project path significantly deviates from the planned one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flexing-through-the-project&quot;&gt;Flexing through the project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing a project incorporates dealing with variations: stakeholders’ attitudes and commitments are mutable and transform over project phases; internal or external business landscape can curve in another direction and strengthen some constraints; minor and big mistakes in planning and estimating show up and many others expected, foreseeable, and unpredictable changes might occur. It is worth setting up reliable systems and processes that allow for identification, analysis, (re)planning, monitoring, controlling, and reacting to variable deviations and changes during the project, and keep focusing on the project’s vision while implementing adjustments. A pronged approach to execution in a combination with system thinking and timely decision-making support conscious flexibility targeted to project success and smoothing out the project path to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of projects is that they are dynamic, changing over time, and reflecting internal and external surroundings. At the same time, they require clear objectives, organization, structure, and processes, profound planning, monitoring and control, committed stakeholders and qualified executors to make targets real. There are a lot of traps and hindrances, including the “onion syndrome” in projects on the way to their success. However, learning, understanding, and practicing in project management aid to overcome obstacles and achieve outstanding results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@svetlana-ilina/the-onion-syndrome-in-projects-7-practical-tips-to-nip-it-in-the-bud-1c5e08d2007d&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="stakeholder" /><category term="processes" /><category term="project-management" /><category term="execution" /><category term="onion-syndrome" /><category term="vision" /><category term="constraints" /><category term="motivation" /><category term="competency" /><category term="commitment" /><category term="team" /><summary type="html">“The art of life is a constant readjustment to our surroundings.” Okakura Kakuzo</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">5 Steps to Make a Successful Project</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Five-steps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 Steps to Make a Successful Project" /><published>2022-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Five-steps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Five-steps/">&lt;p&gt;Professional project handling is a vital success factor for companies. In a time of economic instability, demographic challenges, potent climate change and green agenda, enterprises face the need for internal transformations, exploring new ways of working, and offering novel products and services for their clients. To hit these targets, companies, including those that never dealt with project business before, are forced to dive into project management. Their programs and initiatives have to be managed in an excellent, innovative, and responsible way in order to meet customer expectations and secure a competitive market position. To reach the desired operational excellence in projects, which in most cases is a key to profit and business growth objectives, processes are the starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;start-early&quot;&gt;Start early&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial project stage usually starts during the sales phase. It is well-known for companies that operate in project business. Their project management and sales teams work together to come to an amicable agreement on bids and order releases for projects. This is a highly desirable collaboration because the involvement of a project manager at a very early phase allows them to identify and report any potential risks before a contract is signed. A proper project handover is another cornerstone for a smooth project start. It might save a lot of time and money during the project phases. However, it is not rare that a contract is signed and a project suddenly appears in a backlog of a responsible department with no handover or briefing from the sales team. In an extreme case, a project can start without a project team or even an appointed project manager. This is a daunting situation and an enormous challenge to put such a project on track to meet the requirements set in the contract.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-12-04-pm-phases.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;150%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clarify-the-picture&quot;&gt;Clarify the picture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For internal projects where solutions and services are provided by an organizational unit within a company and project outcomes are to be used internally, the initial stage opens with the clarification of a business case with a scope, time frame, budget, high-level risks, resources, and requirements. Besides these critical aspects, it is also required to set clear project goals and objectives, define acceptance criteria for deliverables, and identify &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholders&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plan-ahead&quot;&gt;Plan ahead&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not matter whether a predictive, adaptive, or hybrid approach better suits a project, planning is a core pillar for its success. Project planning reduces uncertainty, alarms at an early stage of a possible scope creep, and provides a reliable ground to avoid an &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Onion-syndrome/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“onion syndrome”&lt;/a&gt; in projects. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/onion-syndrome.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
The first planning activities are started during an initial project kick-off meeting and followed by an in-depth clarification of the required amount of work; elaboration of a work breakdown structure; definition of a project organization in terms of roles and functions required to fulfill a project’s tasks; reliable estimation of project phases’ durations, costs, resources, and associated risks. It is necessary to define the duration and dependencies of project works, sequence them, identify critical items, a delay of which can collapse the entire project schedule, and plan time reserves. Other important aspects of a project planning are related to stakeholder engagement actions, project communication, and risk management. The mastery of project planning assumes a healthy balance between detailing and generalization: precise and accurate for decisive aspects and shortened or simplified for those that pose a smaller risk and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complexity&lt;/a&gt; for a project. The outcome of this phase is a thoughtful project plan—a solid base for achieving the desired project results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keep-on-track&quot;&gt;Keep on track&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implementation is the longest and often the most dynamic phase of a project. It entails the examination of the viability of different aspects of planning against reality and multiple revisiting of the previous phase for tuning a workable project plan. Besides consistent supervision of work progress, it is crucial to identify any deviations from a project timeline or objectives as early as possible to design, evaluate, and implement corrective actions. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/Boehm-cost-of-change.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
As a rule, the costs of postponed changes are increased exponentially over time. To avoid this situation, a project manager has to drive necessary changes, take in-time decisions, permanently audit the stakeholder landscape, maintain internal and external project communication, and trace risks. Focusing on essential items and rational monitoring of others usually yield a successful project completion and acceptance of its results by clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tighten-loose-ends&quot;&gt;Tighten loose ends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last but not least phase is a project closure. During this phase, all open points should be worked off; project results, the way of its execution, and lessons learned are to be discussed. The desired output of this phase is ideas of how and what can be made better in the next project, and what processes’ improvements can be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A well-thought-out setup of processes with a standing focus on continuous improvement is the prerequisite for getting stable results. It targets delivering excellent performance to customers, lowering risks, and maximizing outcomes. In project management, processes are the starting point and one of the core elements, but they are not a magic pill that guarantees the achievement of outstanding project results. The art of project management incorporates, but goes far beyond processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/5-steps-make-successful-project-svetlana-ilina&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="success-factor" /><category term="processes" /><category term="project-management" /><category term="planning" /><category term="execution" /><category term="onion-syndrome" /><category term="close-out" /><summary type="html">Professional project handling is a vital success factor for companies. In a time of economic instability, demographic challenges, potent climate change and green agenda, enterprises face the need for internal transformations, exploring new ways of working, and offering novel products and services for their clients. To hit these targets, companies, including those that never dealt with project business before, are forced to dive into project management. Their programs and initiatives have to be managed in an excellent, innovative, and responsible way in order to meet customer expectations and secure a competitive market position. To reach the desired operational excellence in projects, which in most cases is a key to profit and business growth objectives, processes are the starting point.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">How to cultivate a “difficult” client</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/difficult-client/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to cultivate a “difficult” client" /><published>2022-11-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/difficult-client</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/difficult-client/">&lt;p&gt;In any work environment, the customer is one of the key factors to set a pivotal way of business development. Sales theory has a long history of tiptoeing around customer needs, customer satisfaction, building trustful relationships, winning customer favor, and resolving problems to ensure an amazing customer experience. In the end, every client wants a product or service that solves their problem, is worth their money and is delivered with outstanding customer service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a service business, besides operational day-to-day activities, unique time-boxed entities aimed to deliver a product/ a service/ a result according to some peculiar customer requirements can be allocated. Each temporary entity is a small project. It has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complexity&lt;/a&gt; and settles on the intersection of the interdependent targets: time, budget, and outputs, and possesses a risk of not achieving some or all of these targets. On the customer side usually exist several involved and affected groups with specific clout. These are &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholders&lt;/a&gt; who can support or block a project and its progress. Often they can be clustered into the categories: decision makers, subject matter experts, and users.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-11-11-stakeholder-groups.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;float:center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a small project, there is no need to use overly complicated instruments to ensure comprehensive identification, analysis, and fuhrer intentional engagement of stakeholders. However, proper stakeholder management without skipping any stages is vital for any project. It helps reduce a project’s complexity by aligning stakeholder expectations on the project’s goals, scope, and deliverables, recognize concealed political games on the customer side that might affect the scope or slay the project. Stakeholder management is a dynamic process that tracks changes in roles, interests, and commitment of involved groups through all project phases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fairness of these statements I’ve learned once again in practice. Recently, a company invited me to take part in their small project with a “very demanding” client. The company is a recognized provider in the talent management market. It has and promotes its own methodology embedded into high-quality products. It was a project with a new client and was supposed to be a door opener for future business. The client is a vast enterprise with a specific corporate culture and established structures, processes, and practices. The project sponsor—one of the new top managers on the client’s side—was familiar with the provider’s products earlier and invited it for the project. The main idea of the project was to replace the existing outdated product on the customer side with a new, deeply customized one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The provider offers different business services and has to deal a lot with product design, customization, and tailoring activities that require handling of basics of project management. The project manager did a good job. The scheduling was brilliant: logical sequencing, workable deadlines, clear milestones, and planned time reserves. An overview of the existing client’s product had enough details to get a complete picture. The features that must be in a new product were defined. The key stakeholders were known. The project team comprised professionals with a dozen years of relevant experience and possessing the expertise for such projects. A progress tracking system was in place. Each member got a piece of work and the execution began. Everything was fine until the first deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, it popped up that the project team and the client had different views on the final product. Even worse, each key stakeholder had her own vision of the product and they provided sometimes opposite comments and suggestions on improvements. Some stakeholders were not aware of or did not realize that the switch to the provider’s methodology would require a change in some working habits. Stakeholders from the users’ group blocked changes in processes. Stakeholders from the experts’ group trusted their own methodology more than the provider’s one. The familiarization of the customer’s experts with the provider’s methodology and users’ training in the new product were not included in the project scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-11-11-credibility-matrix.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;65%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
In most cases, the provider operates in or close to the “ideal” quadrant of the credibility matrix. The company has a solid portfolio of easy-going and demanding clients who acknowledge its expertise and trust in its professional advice. Here, the credibility of the new provider for the client’s experts was not high enough to rely on its expertise, so they requested changes to incorporate their old methodology but damaging the project’s essence. The different compromise attempts entailed a waste of effort through several rounds of reworking. A lot of reworking raised a question about the provider’s expertise in product design and produced an avalanche of new contradictory comments and feedback. The product had a good chance of not passing the quality gates. The company‘s focus drifted from the project margin to the reduction of losses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewed from an observer’s standpoint, it might be noticed that this situation is hardly unique and the hackneyed sales-slogan “one size does not fit all” is undeniably valid for stakeholder management. I am sure that everyone can recall a lot of cases when slipshod stakeholder management created an illusion of stakeholder commitment that subsequently multiplied the complexity of projects and generated problems out of the blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/how-cultivate-difficult-client-svetlana-ilina&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="stakeholder" /><category term="case-study" /><category term="customer" /><category term="risk" /><category term="project-management" /><category term="execution" /><summary type="html">In any work environment, the customer is one of the key factors to set a pivotal way of business development. Sales theory has a long history of tiptoeing around customer needs, customer satisfaction, building trustful relationships, winning customer favor, and resolving problems to ensure an amazing customer experience. In the end, every client wants a product or service that solves their problem, is worth their money and is delivered with outstanding customer service.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Motivation Pulse-Check:a fancy instrument or a call for action tool</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/pulse-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Motivation Pulse-Check:a fancy instrument or a call for action tool" /><published>2022-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/pulse-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/pulse-check/">&lt;p&gt;Within the last decade, employee engagement and motivation have an undeniable impact on any human-related activities within an organization. It hastens the growth of a new market niche and an appearance of new players besides big reputed analytical and consulting companies. The pandemic challenged the tiptoeing around employee engagement and set an ardent trend of a permanent motivation pulse-check. The boom of pulse-checks offered by a variety of providers or designed internally entails that a lot of companies entwine this instrument with their regular HR-toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve interacted with an industrial mid-sized company (app. 3300 FTEs) and one of the discussed topics was a global employee engagement survey. Filled with pride the process owner showed me the following results:
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-08-12-pulse-survey.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not going into details of the index’s calculation, the results for all categories fall into a “good” range, i.e. &amp;gt;50. For sub-categories related to the self-esteem of employees, the results fall into a very high range between 80 and 91, that supports an assumption of the high level of motivation and engagement of the respondences. At first glance, the results are awesome, despite of the slight decrease tendencies for three of the five major categories.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-08-12-pulse-result-chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s inspect what is behind the data and how the company can use the results. A properly designed and applied engagement survey could be a valuable tool to learn what works and what doesn’t work in a company, to develop and tune strategies to better serve business needs and any kind of change. At the same time, there are a lot of pitfalls in using any measuring instrument to get reliable and valid results. The basic idea of this statement can be presented by the well-known target-diagram:
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-08-12-targets.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;float:center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The linchpin of the reliability of any measurable instrument is its design. Reliability means that we are measuring different aspects of a dedicated area. To reach a high level of reliability, it is not a simple task and requires not only knowledge and design skills but also a comprehensive testing activities on a big heterogeneous population. Therefore, for companies with limited design capabilities, it makes sense to consider offers of external providers, rather than develop their own engagement survey. A reliability of a tool is the first pivotal element, without it any follow-up activities turn to pure guessing instead of parsing. In our case, the company has used an engagement survey offered by an external provider and the consistent and narrow spreads of values for sub-categories collaterally support an assumption of its reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second core element of any measurable instrument is its validity. It is a confirmation that we measure what was intended to be measured. Undoubtedly, a design contributes to validity as well, however, a negligent application is a common reason for getting skewed results of a reliable and valid tool. As a consequence, a company spends a lot of money and efforts on wrong activities which do not yield the expected results, if any at all. In our case the company fell into this trap and has a mismatched feeling of the reality and a survey-based analytics.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-08-12-pulse-response-rate.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most critical points for any statistical analysis is a selection of the right sample, if it is not possible to collect data from the entire population. &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/logical-fallacies/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mistakes in sampling&lt;/a&gt; 
 unavoidably lead to biased results. In an organization context with the known and limited population size, all employees have to be included into an engagement survey sample to get valid results of analysis. In the company’s case, the average response rate is low (&amp;lt;50%). It means that most of the company’s employees did not participate in the survey and it does not allow to consider the survey results as valid ones for the whole company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a unique case, rather a typical one which I’ve encountered in my practice. To proceed further, the process owner should give himself an honest answer to the question: “What has this pulse-check been implemented in the company for?” If the main reason is following the dominant trend to have a fancy instrument and its results are not going to be transferred into actions, then everything is done and nice pictures with “the outstanding results” can be shown any time. If the primary interest lies in getting a true-shot of what is going on with the employees’ motivation and engagement in the company and design appropriate nudging actions of improvements, then the first area to work on is the tool’s validity through an increase of the participation rate. This is a daunting but doable task, where the employees are at the center!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/motivation-pulse-check-fancy-instrument-call-action-tool-ilina&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="case-study" /><category term="motivation" /><category term="tool" /><summary type="html">Within the last decade, employee engagement and motivation have an undeniable impact on any human-related activities within an organization. It hastens the growth of a new market niche and an appearance of new players besides big reputed analytical and consulting companies. The pandemic challenged the tiptoeing around employee engagement and set an ardent trend of a permanent motivation pulse-check. The boom of pulse-checks offered by a variety of providers or designed internally entails that a lot of companies entwine this instrument with their regular HR-toolbox.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Project complexity or how to compare apples and oranges</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/project-complexity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project complexity or how to compare apples and oranges" /><published>2022-04-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/project-complexity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/project-complexity/">&lt;p&gt;Nowadays the word ‘project’ is one the most popular and trendy terms. There is a tendency to project everything: from a minor life phase to conquering galaxies. I’m not going to dig into details of misusing the term ‘project’ and ‘project management’ activities associated with it. I would rather stick to the classical project definition and make an attempt to find a way of comparing projects belonging to diverse application areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skyrocketing development of technologies boosts new business segments and secures the importance of project management for a dozen years ahead. A project is a temporary entity aimed to deliver a product, a service, or a result according to a specific business case. It is not an operational activity and has inherent characteristics, which distinguish it from day-to-day business. Each project is unique, lies at the intersection of the three interdependent targets: time, budget, and result(s), and always possesses a risk of not achieving some or all of these targets. It requires a special team or even a project organization to ensure proper management and the desired outcome. And last, but not least: a project has complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-actually-project-complexity&quot;&gt;What is actually project complexity?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are different dimensions affecting the complexity of a project. For example, budget, duration, the intricacy of applied technologies, controllability of key stakeholders, difficulty in handling involved groups with specific clout (contractors, authorities, etc.), the existence of high political risks, and many others, which can be derived from the PESTLE or other comparable analysis techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no unambiguous dimensions for complexity, which are valid for all projects. In practice, each company selects appropriate dimensions and sets its own parameters to complexity to differentiate its projects. Project budget is the most commonly used characteristic of project complexity. For a homogeneous project portfolio, this one-dimension differentiator totally makes sense and works perfectly. However, for a portfolio, which embraces diverse projects from a variety of industries, adhesion to one dimension of complexity will likely lead to a comparison of apples and oranges. It is not an easy task to define complexity by setting practical parameters of comparison for a diversified group of projects. Obviously, several dimensions should be used to emphasize core differences, risks, or critical factors for these projects. Depending on a company’s internal standards a presentation of complexity for heterogeneous projects can be visualized by charts and diagrams, categorized by weighted characteristics, or other approaches might be used to support an illustration of the selected data sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;comparison-of-diverse-projects&quot;&gt;Comparison of diverse projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of any project is its uniqueness. For R&amp;amp;D projects this statement has apparent validity, in other fields project originality assumes a unique combination of phases and features suitable for the specific case. To provide one of the possible ways of comparing totally different projects, I’d like to demonstrate some real-world projects as an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small company with top technical expertise in some niche areas, that designs its own high-tech products and develops exclusive solutions for customers’ projects, has taken a development project for a very specific business case. The project is to be based on one of the emerging technologies. There is no evidence or reference suggesting that the selected technology has ever been applied to similar tasks. However, some key stakeholders on the customer side are excited about this project because its successful results integrated into their own products might give their company a drastic competitive advantage. The estimated project duration is 12-18 months, the planned budget is 0,5 million Euro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge international company with branches in more than 20 countries decides to implement a modern cloud-based recruiting system. This new corporate solution has to replace all local recruiting systems, must be integrated with other HR tools, and is to fully comply with corporate IT policies. Its implementation most probably entails significant changes in corporate and local HR processes. At the same time, a unified solution is to yield a significant cost-saving effect in the future. The project has received support from the company’s top management. The planned project duration is about one year, the estimated budget is around one million Euro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A medium-sized company, that actively cooperates with a lot of contractors good at specific parts of construction work, manages a project to build a small tunnel in a mountain. The tunnel will help to reduce transit traffic intensity in the nearest city. At the same time, this mountain area is inhabited by species whose wellbeing during the construction phase might raise concerns among local environmentalists. The estimated project budget is more than ten million Euro, the estimated duration is 18 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To visualize a possible comparison of the above-mentioned projects I decided to use a well-known bubble chart, which is a common illustrative tool for a data set with two to four dimensions. The first two dimensions are presented as coordinates, the third as bubble-size, and the fourth as color. The beauty of this chart is that depending on your need and available data it is possible to use a two-dimensional picture or extends it to a three- or even four-dimensional presentation of data without sacrificing readability.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-04-04-bubble-chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve selected the following dimensions: budget, technology, and stakeholder. From my point of view, these parameters have eye-catching differences for these projects and can be placed as coordinates and bubble-size to visualize the distinctions. Owing to the availability of quantitative data about the budgets, it is possible to use a discrete numerical scale for this dimension, while some ordinal scales should be applied to the rest. For the fourth dimension I’ve used an estimated probability of the risk, that the project outcome won’t reach one or more targets (results, budget, time), and the simple ordinal scale (low-medium-high) for color-coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These differentiators were chosen based on available project pitches and for illustrative purposes only. The more project details are available, the richer the field of possible dimensions, parameters, scales, and comparison methods becomes. However, before starting a selection of suitable characteristics you should have a clear vision of what you would like to get as a result keeping the intended application in mind. It will help a lot to reduce overdoing and waste of effort during this exciting exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In dealing with diverse projects the reasonable usage of multi-dimensional criteria to highlight project complexity serves as a helpful instrument to get a targeted snapshot of projects’ overview, to monitor and keep a project portfolio balance, and can support in ‘go/ no go’ decision making about new projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/project-complexity-how-compare-apples-oranges-svetlana-ilina&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="case-study" /><category term="project-management" /><summary type="html">Nowadays the word ‘project’ is one the most popular and trendy terms. There is a tendency to project everything: from a minor life phase to conquering galaxies. I’m not going to dig into details of misusing the term ‘project’ and ‘project management’ activities associated with it. I would rather stick to the classical project definition and make an attempt to find a way of comparing projects belonging to diverse application areas.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Critical Issues and Success Factors in HR projects: Stakeholders</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Stakeholders/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Critical Issues and Success Factors in HR projects: Stakeholders" /><published>2022-02-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-02-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Stakeholders</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Stakeholders/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“No matter what you stand for, no matter what your ultimate purpose may be, you must take into account the effects of your actions on others, as well as their potential effects on you.”&lt;/em&gt;  R. Edward Freeman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have received a new challenging task — to lead one of the HR projects. It’s awesome! Congratulations! As the first excitement wears off, you are to decide: &lt;em&gt;Where and how to start? What factors, aspects, and specifics should be considered?&lt;/em&gt; — and dozens of other questions and points to fulfill the requirements of your project. I’m not going to compete with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pmi.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PMI&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.axelos.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Axelos&lt;/a&gt; in providing a comprehensive methodology in project management, rather give some practitioner tips on what matters to HR project success and list some valuable sources where to glean further hints and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, an &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/PM-HR_strangers-or-buddies/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HR project&lt;/a&gt; is initiated as a response to changes in business strategy, a value-added HR initiative, digitalization of processes, or any combination of these. HR projects are diverse by purpose, nature, duration, available resources, and budget. However, some common critical issues and roadblocks can be present in any HR project (Figure 1). 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-02-04-Figure1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
An encounter with some of them might require significant efforts and additional resources to get a project back on track while facing the full set will most probably prove fatal for project success. On the other hand, proper conscious preventive activities and skillful management empower one to turn these hindrances into powerful project drivers and success factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such factor is stakeholders, i.e. groups, persons, authorities, or parties that might have a vested interest in any phase of a project, program, or initiative. Careless or slipshod stakeholder management can bury any project or significantly multiply its complexity. HR projects are not an exception to this general rule. It is well known that even minor changes related to humans might have huge and unforeseen effects. HR projects are dedicated to and dealing with people. Sometimes it is not easy to predict the entire range of potential reactions of the affected groups and individuals and build up a complete overview of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stakeholder-identification&quot;&gt;Stakeholder identification&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first core step to success in any project is the proper identification of stakeholders. There is a wider range of stakeholders which may affect, or be affected by, an HR project. These stakeholders may be internal or external to a company and may become supporters or blockers of the project and its progress. For most HR projects, there is a need for involvement of other departments, such as IT, finance, communication, etc., that favor classification of stakeholders into the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;upward&lt;/strong&gt; (sponsor, steering committee),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;downward&lt;/strong&gt; (project team and contributing experts),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;outward&lt;/strong&gt; (providers, employees, regulators) and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sideward&lt;/strong&gt; (peers who collaborate in sharing resources and/or information).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not a secret that some HR projects in big corporations have a complex network of relationships and hidden political games in their project scopes. For these projects, it makes sense to use more complex instruments to ensure comprehensive identification and further intentional engagement of stakeholders. One of these instruments is the salience model (Figure 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-02-04-Figure2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It suggests that &lt;em&gt;“the question of stakeholder salience — the degree to which managers give priority to competing stakeholder claims — goes beyond the question of stakeholder identification, because the dynamics inherent in each relationship involve complex considerations”&lt;/em&gt; (Mitchell, R.; Agle B.; Wood, D. 1997). According to this model, stakeholders are classified based on the relative absence or presence of all or some of the three attributes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;power&lt;/strong&gt; (level of authority or the ability to bring about the outcomes they desire),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;legitimacy&lt;/strong&gt; (ones who “really count”),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;urgency&lt;/strong&gt; (need for immediate attention).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholders disposed of only one attribute are belonging to the group of latent stakeholders (dormant, discretionary, demanding). This group is worth identifying. However, any special attention and engagement actions to these stakeholders are not likely to be given. The group of expectant stakeholders (dominant, dangerous, dependent) comprises those with two attributes which in most cases lead to an active stance of stakeholders and requires thoughtful analysis and actions from a project team. By acquiring the missing third attribute, any expectant stakeholder can become a definitive stakeholder. This should be carefully tracked, monitored, and reflected in communication and engagement activities by a project team. Thus, the level of engagement between an HR project manager and expectant stakeholders is to be higher compared to latent ones or the same as required for the group of definitive stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholder identification is a dynamic process due to classification attributes being a variable that can change for any particular entity and over time, presenting a constructed reality, and a matter of multiple perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stakeholder-analysis&quot;&gt;Stakeholder analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholder analysis is a pillar of stakeholder management and serves as a bridge between stakeholder identification and stakeholder engagement. Often, stakeholders have primary drivers in political, economical, social, technical, and legal fields, which determine their levels of interest in a project. Another important characteristic is the impact or the degree of a stakeholder’s influence on project phases and the final result. These two dimensions provide the basis for the stakeholder analysis and help to rank stakeholders and map them to different groups, for example, actively manage, manage, actively inform and inform. At the next stage, appropriate engagement and communication measures should be elaborated and implemented for each group of stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some projects with matted relationships between stakeholders, there is a need for an additional dimension, for example, level of authority, and/or weighting of applied characteristics to improve the depiction of a stakeholder community. The result of analysis for most HR projects can be presented in a form of a two-dimensional matrix or a three-dimensional cube, aimed at focusing productive efforts of a project team on critical sub-sets of stakeholders. It is worth noting that the characteristics of a stakeholder are not once and constantly fixed values. They do not have a steady state and are often changing over project phases. These changes find a reflection in altering engagement levels of different stakeholders, which can be traced by a so-called stakeholder engagement assessment matrix. The matrix provides a comparison between the current and the desired support levels of a project by stakeholders. Depending on the project’s specifics, any appropriate nominal or ordinal scale might be used to categorize the support levels. The assessment results indicate outliers within the previously identified groups of stakeholders to finetune engagement and communication activities for groups and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Causes of a stakeholder’s attitude changes can be found in a psychological domain scrutinized by various scientists and practitioners over the last century. The landscape of psychological theories is multifarious and provides a fruitful basis for further development of new models and frameworks and a broad room for its application (Figure 3). 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-02-04-Figure3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
For example, the iceberg model can help to rationalize some unexpected changes in a stakeholder’s behavior. According to this model, the invisible part of human internal drivers is significantly deeper than the visible one. It comprises multiple layers, which in most cases are not purposively demonstrated, but can be triggered at any moment. This is one reason why, a stakeholder might spring up during the project implementation, which can negatively impact the timing, scope, or resources of the project. Another plausible reason is that this stakeholder most probably had that opinion before, but you just did not know it or did not pay enough attention to sustain and develop his commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stakeholder-engagement&quot;&gt;Stakeholder engagement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholder engagement is another important component of stakeholder management that ensures the productive involvement of stakeholders in decision making and project execution, according to their needs, interests, and impact. The ultimate engagement goal is to build and maintain the continued commitment of stakeholders during all project phases by instrumentally managing expectations, addressing risks and concerns, clarifying and resolving issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commitment is the clue that tacks people and the project results. It is an intangible, but noticeable and altering substance, which might be difficult to obtain and easy to lose. The development of stakeholder commitment usually follows the sequential stages of the commitment curve and passes through the main phases: preparation, acceptance, commitment (Figure 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-02-04-Figure4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model depicts the critical stages where a stakeholder perception might change from the supportive mode to a blocking one or return to earlier stages, as stakeholders learn more about the project and what it will require from them or give them. Obviously, each stakeholder has an individual commitment curve, which might have a minor or significant deviation from the average pace of the assigned stakeholder group. It explains the appearance of outliers within the classified stakeholder groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altering commitment can be another reason for a stakeholder’s attitude changes and the further necessity to allocate stakeholders to different groups during the project. It also proves the necessity to intentionally monitor and analyze revealed changes, and adapt planned stakeholder engagement and communication activities respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stakeholder-communication&quot;&gt;Stakeholder communication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communication is tightly embedded in the stakeholder engagement process and serves as its engine. It is vitally important for an HR project success to select appropriate methods for delivering the first contact messages to stakeholders, as this is a prerequisite to creating an awareness of the project. There is a wide range of options including a company’s internal media, memos, staff meetings, personal contact, and other mechanisms to launch a forward movement through the stakeholder commitment curve. However, communication efforts do not always produce progress toward the next stages in the way of stakeholder commitment. It is so frustrating when, after many meetings and memos about an initiative, some stakeholders either are not prepared for it or react with total surprise when it affects them. In order to diminish a misunderstanding and possible resistance, proper communication to different stakeholders through relevant channels should be started as early as possible, be transparent, adaptive, clear, and precise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ginger up the efficiency of internal and external communications, it is worth thinking over a stakeholder communication plan. Depending on the project complexity and a variety of the identified stakeholder groups, it can be highly detailed or broadly framed. An effective communication plan contains details of what information the project management team will send to, and receive from different stakeholder groups, through what channels information is to be distributed, and how often each stakeholder group is to be approached. As a general rule for HR projects, flexibility and incorporating stakeholder feedback into communications are to prevail over a formal following of the activities that were initially fixed in the communication plan. The stakeholder communication plan is dynamic and a subject of constant changes to address new challenges and issues popping up during a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High stakeholders’ commitment and involvement can propel any HR project to the sky, while lack of stakeholder support will tank even a brilliant HR initiative. Stakeholder management is exciting, but a tricky process, which requires continuous attention through all project phases. It is likely to be the first project management area to start with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Freeman, R. Edward, (1984). 
&lt;em&gt;Strategic Management: A Stakeholder Approach.&lt;/em&gt; Boston: Pitman.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Freeman, R. Edward, (2004). 
&lt;em&gt;The Stakeholder Approach Revisited.&lt;/em&gt; Zeitschrift für Wirtschafts- und Unternehmensethik, 5(3), pp. 228-254.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mitchell, R., Agle B., Wood, D., (1997). 
&lt;em&gt;Toward a Theory of Stakeholder Identification and Salience: Defining the Principle of Who and What Really Counts.&lt;/em&gt; The Academy of Management Review, 22(4), pp. 853-886.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conner, Daryl R.; Patterson, Robert W. (1982). 
&lt;em&gt;Building Commitment to Organizational Change.&lt;/em&gt; Training &amp;amp; Development Journal, Vol 36(4), pp. 18-30.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Conner Partners, (2018). 
&lt;em&gt;Building Commitment to Organizational Change.&lt;/em&gt; www.connerpartners.com&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Project Management Institute (2017, 2021). 
&lt;em&gt;A Guide to the Project Management Body of Knowledge (PMBOK® Guide).&lt;/em&gt; Sixth and Seventh Editions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Axelos. (2017). 
&lt;em&gt;Managing Successful Projects with PRINCE2®.&lt;/em&gt; Sixth Edition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://svetlana-ilina.medium.com/critical-issues-and-success-factors-in-hr-projects-stakeholders-e14a405aef9a&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="stakeholder" /><category term="hr-project" /><category term="risk" /><category term="success-factor" /><category term="communication" /><category term="commitment" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="project-management" /><summary type="html">“No matter what you stand for, no matter what your ultimate purpose may be, you must take into account the effects of your actions on others, as well as their potential effects on you.” R. Edward Freeman</summary></entry></feed>