<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-06-12T15:54:25+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/feed.xml</id><title type="html">agile people management</title><subtitle>A miscellany of real stories, ideas and thoughts about people management, project management and their interconnection in the fields of corporate human resources, digitalization, organizational and change management</subtitle><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Continue the hunt for the root cause</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/RCA-quantitative-methods/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Continue the hunt for the root cause" /><published>2024-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/RCA-quantitative-methods</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/RCA-quantitative-methods/">&lt;p&gt;Finding the root cause is not a trivial task. Often, seemingly obvious causes of a problem lay far away from the most essential one. The plentiful cluster of &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/RCA-qualitative-methods/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;qualitative methods&lt;/a&gt;  for root cause analysis can help a problem-solver identify possible reasons why a poser might happen. Another powerful cluster of quantitative methods naturally supplements qualitative ones and targets to validate and prove assumptions based on formalized mathematical argumentation. The variety of quantitative methods that support the root cause analysis can be split into two major categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;graphical analysis, which is based on descriptive statistics and, besides the identification of causes, provides a great visual reinforcement for the further communication process;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in-depth statistical analysis, that mainly serves as a validator of possible causes identified by other tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;graphical-analysis&quot;&gt;Graphical analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of analysis focuses on describing and analyzing the key characteristics of a dataset without generalizing to a larger population. There are plenty of tools (for example, Excel) that allow a problem-solver to produce various illustrations without advanced statistical knowledge. Charts assist in visualizing the numbers and their types are selected based on the purpose of analysis and the message to be conveyed. There are four basic types of graphs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bar charts aimed to summarize quantities of different categories;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;histogram charts applied to display the frequency distribution of data points;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;line charts used to show trends over time;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pie charts assigned to illustrate numerical proportions of the whole.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphical instruments have different complexity in creation and understanding. Duly selected charts are valuable add-ons in parsing root causes. Numeric data representing items one can count in separate units without fractional or decimal values, like the number of customers, is called discrete data. They are usually illustrated by Pareto charts, pie charts, and bar charts. Continuous data, which can be measured using a scale and meaningfully split into smaller parts, like temperature, time, or weight, is best visualized in histograms, box plots, and in the form of run and control charts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pareto-charts&quot;&gt;Pareto charts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pareto charts are one of the most well-known and mass-applied tools in problem-solving and decision-making. It is a graphical representation of elements in a ranked bar chart. The main idea behind this is the Pareto Principle, named after Italian economist Vilfredo Pareto, or so-called the &lt;strong&gt;80/20 rule&lt;/strong&gt;. It stays that 80% of consequences come from 20% of the causes. In other words, a few elements create more impact than all the other causes and a problem-solver can usually identify three to four causes that, if eliminated or improved, will have a crucial impact on the issue.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2024/2024-06-12-RCA-pareto.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
For example, data collected during exit interviews is worth visualizing as the Pareto chart. Among the revealed top causes that triggered employees’ decisions to leave a company, a problem-solver may select one, not necessarily the first on the top, to elaborate an action plan to fix this cause and observe how the situation will develop. The decision in which order to tackle the key causes depends on a variety of factors, like the complexity of the realization, available resources, and so on.
Besides strong analytical support, Pareto charts show complex data in a simple visual format that prevents misunderstanding of presented information and reduces tiptoeing around discovered causes. It allows to narrow an approach for a problem that has multiple causes or is too broad to address in a single change action. This method can be used separately to spot the causes of an issue or be effectively combined with other qualitative and quantitative methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;box-plots&quot;&gt;Box plots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A box plot is a concise way of presenting a dataset by displaying the maximum, the minimum, the average, and the medians of the lower half and the upper half of the dataset. Box plots are often called Box-and-Whisker graphs, where the box is drawn from the median of the lower half to the median of the upper half, the whiskers indicate extremes of the dataset, and the dots are outliers. The line within the box is the average of the dataset.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2024/2024-06-12-RCA-boxplot.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
In a given example, the data show days on sick leave of various employees within a period. The results are divided into two categories based on attendance of fitness. Even without further explanation, it can be said that employees who practice sports took on average fewer days on sick leave during the selected period than ones, who did not attend fitness. So there might be a causal relationship between attending fitness programs and the wellness of employees. If a company aims to reduce the average sick leave days of its employees, including fitness programs as a perk in a well-being package can be a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphical analysis is useful for gaining an idea about data relationships and is powerful for illustrating findings to others, but in-depth statistical analysis helps to understand relationships with more certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;statistical-analysis&quot;&gt;Statistical analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistical analysis is the process of collecting and investigating large volumes of quantitative data to identify trends, patterns, and relationships and to obtain valuable insights. There are two main statistical methods applied to data analysis: descriptive and inferential statistics. In business analytics and data science, both methods are used to support research, validate theories, and study complex data relationships and entail some statistical computing usually done with the help of specialized software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Descriptive statistics&lt;/strong&gt; deals with summarizing, organizing, and meaningfully presenting data of a given dataset. The results of the analysis are conveyed as charts, graphs, or tables, and it goes far beyond the simple graphical analysis mentioned above. The principal focuses of descriptive statistics lay on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measures of frequency: count, percent, and frequency;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measures of central tendency: mean, median, and mode;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measures of dispersion: range, variance, skewness, and standard deviation;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;measures of position: percentiles, quartiles, and interquartiles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While descriptive statistics conclude without generalization to a bigger population, &lt;strong&gt;inferential statistics&lt;/strong&gt; aim to apply the results of analysis based on the selected dataset or sample across the entire population. The relevance and quality of the sample are vital for the reliability of conclusions. To get valid results that support the root cause analysis, most times a problem-solver applies the probability sampling method, which utilizes some form of random selection. Depending on the characteristics of the population, one of the four basic probability sampling types is run: simple random sampling, systematic sampling, stratified sampling, or cluster sampling. A sample size must be chosen to accurately represent the population and be sufficiently large to yield statistically significant findings. In a business environment, it should provide a balance between statistical validity and practical feasibility, including constraints of time, budget, and the target population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hypothesis-testing&quot;&gt;Hypothesis testing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hypothesis testing is a method of statistical inference used to decide whether or not the data rejects a particular assumption and involves a calculation of a test statistic. It makes conclusions about the population based on data from a sample. For example, during a brainstorming session to reveal the causes of a high fluctuation rate of top performers was assumed that the pay-for-performance principle does not work in a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure a proper alignment between pay and performance, a company must consider all pay elements: annual base pay, annual incentives, performance-related cash/ shares/ stocks, other equity, and perks. Employees in a company might be entitled to various combinations of pay elements. At the same time, all employees have annual income, and usually, its change is a part of the annual performance review discussion. So, it can be checked if there is a link between the performance results of employees with adjustments of their total annual compensation. Parsing can be done for all employees in small and mid-sized companies, but big enterprises with thousands of employees face time and budget limitations for analysis and cannot examine the whole population. So, to proceed with testing, a reliable sample of 200+ entities is to be constructed. It is worth considering that different job families might have diverse compensation structures (for example, proportions of base and variable pay). Therefore, to get a sample that best represents the entire population, stratification can be applied. In other words, one selects random entities from each job family. Every element in this stratified sample will possess two characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an individual performance result assigned to one of the performance categories (usually up to 5 categories, e.g.: needs improvement, partially meets expectations, meets expectations, partially exceeds expectations, exceeds expectations),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a change in annual compensation compared to the previous year. An adjustment makes sense to measure in percentage because salary levels often have noticeable variations for different locations. Dealing with multiple currencies may require some norming methods to apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start the analysis, the null hypothesis (&lt;em&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;) and the opposite alternative one (&lt;em&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;) have to be set. Here, the hypotheses can be formulated as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;: Individual performance does not affect the change of an individual’s annual compensation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt;: Individual performance affects the change in an individual’s annual compensation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, hypothesis testing can examine distributions of two dimensions: a performance category and a percentage of change in annual compensation. Based on observations of these variables, the null hypothesis of their independence can be checked with a &lt;strong&gt;chi-squared test&lt;/strong&gt;. This procedure leads to the determination whether &lt;em&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; can be rejected. As the conclusion is based on the sample and not the entire population, there is always some risk of error. A &lt;strong&gt;type I error&lt;/strong&gt; corresponds with the probability of rejecting &lt;em&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; when the null hypothesis is true (α), and a &lt;strong&gt;type II error&lt;/strong&gt; reflects the probability of accepting the null hypothesis when &lt;em&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is false (β). To conduct analysis, a problem-solver specifies the maximum allowable probability of making a type I error, called the level of significance for the test. Common choices for the level of significance are α=0.05 and α=0.01. Another important element in hypothesis testing is the observed level of significance to the test (&lt;em&gt;p-value&lt;/em&gt;). It measures how likely it is that any observed difference between groups is because of chance. The &lt;em&gt;p-value&lt;/em&gt; is calculated under the selected statistical test and then compared with the chosen α: if the &lt;em&gt;p-value&lt;/em&gt; is less than α, the null hypothesis can be rejected, and the statistical conclusion is that the alternative hypothesis is accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;correlation-and-regression-analysis&quot;&gt;Correlation and regression analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regression analysis is the most effective method for constructing a model of the relationship between a dependent variable and one or more independent variables. Various tests are then employed to determine if the model is satisfactory to predict the value of the dependent variable given values for the independent ones. A &lt;strong&gt;simple linear regression analysis&lt;/strong&gt; estimates parameters in a linear equation that can describe the relationship between a single dependent variable (possibly output) and a single independent variable (possibly input) and predict how one variable might behave given changes in another variable. However, the changes don’t necessarily indicate a cause, only that the variables are intertwined in some way. Often, the results of a simple linear regression analysis are presented as a scatterplot with the regression line and the regression function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regression analysis is tightly linked to &lt;strong&gt;correlation analysis&lt;/strong&gt;. They both examine the same relationship between two quantitative variables from different angles. Regression investigates a form of the relationship and correlation provides information on the strength and direction of this relationship. The most frequently used is the so-called “Pearson’s correlation” (&lt;em&gt;r&lt;/em&gt;). To get it, divide the covariance of two variables by the product of their standard deviations. The Pearson correlation is &lt;em&gt;+1&lt;/em&gt; in the case of a perfect positive (increasing) linear relationship, &lt;em&gt;−1&lt;/em&gt; in the case of a perfect decreasing (negative) linear relationship (so-called, &lt;em&gt;anti-correlation&lt;/em&gt;), and some value between &lt;em&gt;−1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;+1&lt;/em&gt; in all other cases, indicating the degree of linear dependence between the variables. As it approaches zero, there is less of a relationship (closer to uncorrelated). The closer the coefficient is to either &lt;em&gt;−1&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;+1&lt;/em&gt;, the stronger the correlation between the variables. The correlation coefficient measures only the degree of linear association between two variables. Any conclusions on a cause-and-effect relationship rely on a problem-solver’s judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correlation and linear regression are commonly employed techniques to explore the relationship between two quantitative variables. Usually, correlation analysis is conducted first, and with the confirmed relationship, its model is examined by regression analysis. For example, there is a need to analyze if a company grants performance-related equity in line with the performance results of organizational units. Following the main idea of the pay-for-performance concept, there is an assumption that managers entitled to performance-related stocks from better-performing units should be awarded bigger amounts of equity compared to their peers from less-performing business units. To verify this idea, a population of around 350 managers eligible for performance-related stocks from 16 units was taken. For this population was parsed a correlation between the percentages of weighted BU-target achievements and normed averages of allocated amounts per manager in the respective unit within the last five years.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2024/2024-06-12-RCA-correlation.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;120%&quot; style=&quot;float:center&quot; /&gt;
The analysis yields the following results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nine organizational units have a strong positive correlation between their performance and allocated stock reward (&lt;em&gt;r &amp;gt; 0.6&lt;/em&gt;), which corresponds to the pay-for-performance principle;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two units have a strong negative correlation between their performance and stock reward (&lt;em&gt;r &amp;lt; -0.6&lt;/em&gt;). It is necessary to investigate the reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;four units have weak correlation (&lt;em&gt;-0.5 &amp;lt; r &amp;lt; 0.5&lt;/em&gt;), which means these BUs’ performance is not the key factor for their equity allocation;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the calculated weighted average correlation between BU performance and the average amount of equity allocation on a company level is not strong (&lt;em&gt;r = 0.45&lt;/em&gt;), so regression analysis can be skipped.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, an additional correlation between two data sets with the shifted starting point has also been calculated. For this delayed correlation the first variable (BU-performance) was used for the data set for four years: from (20XX-5) to (20XX-1), as the second variable (allocated average amount per manager) was applied to the data set from (20XX-4) to 20XX. This parsing shows a strong delayed correlation for one unit, i.e. there is a tendency to correct stocks’ allocation for this BU considering its performance in the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results allow us to conclude that the pay-for-performance concept is not equally applied across units in the company. To strengthen the relationship between the granted stocks and units’ performance on a company level an action plan should include digging into specific situations of business units from the weak and strong negative correlation areas to determine other factors influencing the process of stocks’ distribution and possible causes that hinder the application of the pay-for-performance principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantitative methods are powerful instruments to make educated decisions about processes, data relationships, and causes, and they are not limited to the described ones. The palette of quantitative analysis is very diverse in terms of complexity, frequency of usage, and application areas. The growth of the importance and popularity of big data spurs an interest in quantitative methods of analysis and sprawls the landscape of statistical software. Besides the traditional SPSS, Stata, and Minitab, nowadays the market offers a lot of other commercial and open-source programs, as well as boosts the development of programming languages suitable for statistical computing and graphics, like R, Python, and so on. Appropriate software significantly saves time for a problem-solver and eases the computing of complicated tests and analyses, but does not substitute the necessity of understanding statistical methods and their thoughtful usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/continue-hunt-root-cause-svetlana-ilina-f2e2c/?trackingId=qimrKqOu9gyx28JdSfxWqg%3D%3D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="problem" /><category term="problem-solving" /><category term="root-cause" /><category term="method" /><category term="tool" /><category term="statistics" /><category term="Pareto" /><summary type="html">Finding the root cause is not a trivial task. Often, seemingly obvious causes of a problem lay far away from the most essential one. The plentiful cluster of qualitative methods for root cause analysis can help a problem-solver identify possible reasons why a poser might happen. Another powerful cluster of quantitative methods naturally supplements qualitative ones and targets to validate and prove assumptions based on formalized mathematical argumentation. The variety of quantitative methods that support the root cause analysis can be split into two major categories: graphical analysis, which is based on descriptive statistics and, besides the identification of causes, provides a great visual reinforcement for the further communication process; in-depth statistical analysis, that mainly serves as a validator of possible causes identified by other tools.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">In pursuit of the root cause</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/RCA-qualitative-methods/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In pursuit of the root cause" /><published>2023-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/RCA-qualitative-methods</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/RCA-qualitative-methods/">&lt;p&gt;Your organization has lost a tender again. A chief engineer left a company on short notice. A number of defective products exceeded the day limit. Projects perennially fail to meet planned time and budget targets. You’ve received a reclamation from one of your customers… Sounds familiar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list of situations when the result differs from the desired performance can be easily extended. Some of these issues require known actions to level out immediate negative effects on business, others should be carefully investigated and analyzed to come up with a suitable solution. At the same time, there is an important similarity in such problems — all of them usually have a cause or a set of causes that procure a deviation of an outcome from the wanted one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding the causes of the issue is a challenging task. However, its successful accomplishment makes it easier to identify solutions during the &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Effective-problem-solving/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;problem-solving&lt;/a&gt; process. There is a vast array of methods, tools, and techniques that aim to uncover the causes of problems. They are combined under the common term “&lt;strong&gt;root cause analysis&lt;/strong&gt;” (RCA). Some of them are more general, others are dedicated to specific situations and require a deep understanding of a method and its application area from a problem-solver. Besides the identification of possible causes, RCA tools allow the definition of actions to fix the issue or to prevent it from occurring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big domain of qualitative methods can be used as starters during brainstorming sessions and aid in pinpointing issues and formulating the principal problem. Four of them are described below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-5-whys&quot;&gt;The 5 Whys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a rapid and simple technique to identify causes through the exploration of direct cause-and-effect relationships. It was originally developed and applied by the Toyota Motor Corporation. Today, it is a part of standard problem-solving techniques used by Kaizen, Lean, and Six Sigma professionals. The primary goal of this method is to determine the root cause of a problem by five times repeating the increasingly granular “Why?”-question about a problem or process. In most cases, the answer to the fifth “Why?” is the root cause. Sometimes the questioning requires the next Why-iterations to get to the root cause. To perform this analysis, it is necessary to see a problem, obtain the facts, and grasp the situation’s details. A hypothetical application scenario can be the following:
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/RCA-5whys.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem: &lt;strong&gt;Reclamations from customers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q1: Why do customers write reclamations?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Because customers are not satisfied with services. Other options: quality of products, project delays, or another fact mentioned in reclamations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q2: Why are customers unhappy with our service?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Because customers have to repeat their issue from the very beginning after each call handover from one operator to another. Other options: long waiting time on the line, unclear instructions from an operator of a call center, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q3: Why do operators not capture inquiry details?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: Because it is written in their instructions that only the inquiry topic must be specified in the tracking system. Other options: inquiry details is not a mandatory field to capture, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q4: Why is it not mentioned in the instructions that inquiry details have to be captured in the system as well?&lt;/em&gt;
A: Because there is no dedicated field for it in the system. Other options: to capture details will increase the average time per call, operators are not incentivized by quality of calls, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q5: Why is the tracking system designed this way?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A: (this answer is to be the root cause of the problem)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be clearly seen that the result of this analysis highly depends on the knowledge base of a problem-solver, his ability to avoid &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/logical-fallacies/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;reasoning fallacies&lt;/a&gt;  and dig to the root cause, rather than symptoms. Obviously, different people using it may come up with different causes for the same issue. Therefore, the outcome should be validated. Nevertheless, the 5 Whys is a great brainstorming instrument to seek causes and can be effectively combined with other RCA tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-fishbone-diagram&quot;&gt;The fishbone diagram&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cause-effect diagram, the fishbone diagram, and the Ishikawa diagram are the titles of the same tool. It is based on the principle of simple causality and aims to identify possible causes of an issue. Using this method during brainstorming sessions encourages team members to generate ideas about likely problem causes and organize them in a systematic manner. To give an impetus to analysis and make collaboration more productive, information is usually grouped into the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People&lt;/strong&gt;/ Manpower — causes induced by anyone who carries out or interacts with different aspects of an issue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;/ Procedures — the way things are done, whether by written documents or unwritten rules.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Machines&lt;/strong&gt;/ Technology — causes summoned by equipment and specifics of applied technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measurement&lt;/strong&gt;/ Medium — matters caused by improper or poorly chosen measurement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Materials&lt;/strong&gt;/ Information — causes that appeared because of defects in raw materials or wrong inputs into processes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environment&lt;/strong&gt; is the immediate area surrounding the problem, like humidity, temperature, and other essential physical factors or culture, working climate, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management&lt;/strong&gt; — causes produced by poor leadership and management mistakes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintenance&lt;/strong&gt; — issues caused by inappropriate maintenance.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/RCA-Ishikawa.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;160%&quot; style=&quot;float:center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fishbone diagram originates from the quality domain in a manufacturing environment. In lean production, the &lt;strong&gt;5Ms&lt;/strong&gt; (Manpower, Machines, Methods, Materials, Measurement) is one of the most utilized frameworks for root-cause analysis. The great adaptivity of this method allows a problem-solver to use it in other organizational areas by expanding or shrinking the number of categories and tuning their meanings to fit the specifics of a business field. The process of creating the diagram includes the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On a whiteboard (physical or one in a collaboration tool) sketch a basic fishbone shape and write a summarized version of the defined problem where the fish’s head should be.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Define major categories and their headings. Try to reduce overlap between categories. Draw a fish spine and connectors. Label each connector.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Explain categories to the team, brainstorm suggestions, and distribute them into the categories. Suggestions that fit to more than one category are to be duplicated and placed on the respective branches. It is helpful to write ideas on sticky notes (physical or virtual ones) to be flexible in rearranging them across the fish skeleton.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To ensure the detailed examination of the problem, use &lt;strong&gt;the 5 Whys&lt;/strong&gt; technique for each category of the diagram.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Review the outcome, discuss ideas: placement on the branches, priority, and the probability of being a cause, and make required corrections in the diagram.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Assess the branches that have the biggest impact and circle options that are likely to be root causes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Plan further investigations of the marked causes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method is commonly applied in a reactive modus to trace the root cause(s) of the existing problem. It can be also used as a valuable add-on for product design to analyze trends and prevent potential pitfalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;barrier-analysis&quot;&gt;Barrier analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method has a dual purpose: to understand why a problem happened and how to prevent it. Barrier analysis is derived from and commonly applied in health and safety management to reduce workplace injuries. It may also be used for other areas where risk analysis and prevention play an essential role. This is a relatively simple technique that does not require a lot of resources for successful completion. If a problem-solver has a deep understanding of an issue and its environment, the analysis can be performed solo, otherwise, team brainstorming is a better option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three key elements of barrier analysis are the target, the hazard, and the barrier. Therefore, this method is also known as Target-Hazard-Barrier analysis.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/RCA-barrier-analysis.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The target&lt;/strong&gt; is something that is being selected to be fulfilled or protected (a person performing a job, quality of a product, outcome of a project, etc.). It needs to be maintained under a set of specific requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A hazard&lt;/strong&gt; is a way to harm the target or a cause that hurts it. Hazards are derived from various categories associated with the workplace (safety, physical, ergonomic, psychological, etc.), business risks (strategic, regulatory, financial, operational, reputational, etc.), or other threats concerning the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A barrier&lt;/strong&gt; prevents a negative effect from occurring and provides control over the hazard. Effectiveness of protection has a lot of variations and depends on types, design, and amount of barriers, the chosen solutions to prevent the problem, defined standards and industry best practices, lessons learned from previous incidents, and so on. A single barrier provides one layer of protection for the target, which is taken as a physical, procedural, or individual action. Sometimes, there is a need for multiple layers to defend against failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reliability of this method can be significantly increased by combining it with other RCA techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-questioning-method-5w2h&quot;&gt;The questioning method (5W2H)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is another efficient brainstorming technique to start problem diagnostics and draft directions for further analyses. The questioning method comprises the three main stages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Description of the initial issue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Separation of the principal problem from the secondary ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suggestions on countermeasures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iteratively applied tool allows decomposition of an issue and collects precise problems’ descriptions. Systematic questioning addresses a challenge from different angles, intending to reveal the causes. To use this method, the following questions should be answered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;What&lt;/em&gt; (problem description)?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who&lt;/em&gt; (involved stakeholders)?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where&lt;/em&gt; (the place/ process)?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;When&lt;/em&gt; (the moment, the duration, and the frequency)?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt; (the methods and the manners)?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How many&lt;/em&gt; (the means, the equipment, and the material)?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why&lt;/em&gt; (the reasons, the causes, and the objectives)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no strict order to answer the questions. If a team cannot provide a specific response for one inquiry, it can be skipped and the next question should be addressed. As the principal problem and its environment become clearer, visibility of other answers grows. To spot details on a granular level, some questions should be repeated in incremental series with a focus on possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplicity of this method ensures that a facilitator can use general problem-solving skills to guide a brainstorming. Besides defining, analyzing, and mapping a problem the 5W2H is widely used for conflict resolutions, during project planning sessions, and different types of prospecting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The landscape of qualitative methods is not bounded by the techniques described above. It is continuously developed and enriched by novel approaches and complementary tools. To properly assess and validate findings and strengthen the results of root cause analysis, different techniques should be combined and supplemented by [quantitative methods]/si/en/RCA-quantitative-methods/){:target=”_blank”}.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/pursuit-root-cause-svetlana-ilina-dq9xf%3FtrackingId=ki4%252B3UNiReuo6cCficQZsQ%253D%253D/?trackingId=ki4%2B3UNiReuo6cCficQZsQ%3D%3D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="problem" /><category term="problem-solving" /><category term="root-cause" /><category term="method" /><category term="tool" /><summary type="html">Your organization has lost a tender again. A chief engineer left a company on short notice. A number of defective products exceeded the day limit. Projects perennially fail to meet planned time and budget targets. You’ve received a reclamation from one of your customers… Sounds familiar?</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Effective problem solving</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Effective-problem-solving/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Effective problem solving" /><published>2023-11-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Effective-problem-solving</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Effective-problem-solving/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“One should never impose one’s views on a problem; one should rather study it, and in time a solution will reveal itself.”&lt;/em&gt;  Albert Einstein&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every day there are plenty of situations in which we confront problems, challenges, and routine choices when we want something and do not know immediately what should be accomplished to get it. The desired outcome may be very tangible or abstract. It may be specific or quite general. To obtain relevant results, some physical actions, perceptual and mental activities are required. Simple tasks can be solved without fixating on the methods and necessary steps to reach the result. In complicated situations, there is a need for conscious activities to achieve the desired outcome. A problem-solver has to interact with the situation by appropriately using different cognitive skills and adapting the behavior to the issue specifics. According to Newell and Simon, there are two fundamental problem-solving approaches to apply:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the recognition method&lt;/strong&gt;, when a task is decomposed into small known sub-problems;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the generate and test method&lt;/strong&gt;, which is based on invention and outside-the-box thinking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking is the salient point of problem solving and refers to cognitive activities to focus on specific information, process it, discover connections, make decisions, create fresh ideas, validate them, and integrate novel experiences into existing understanding and perception of how things are. These activities are often categorized as lower- and higher-order thinking skills.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/Bloom-taxonomy.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;120%&quot; style=&quot;float:center&quot; /&gt;
Besides this taxonomy, there are a lot of other commonly used types of thinking skills, which can be classified:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by opposing categories: concrete thinking vs. abstract thinking, convergent thinking vs. divergent thinking, sequential thinking vs. holistic thinking, etc.;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by approaches: systems thinking, critical thinking, analytical thinking, creative thinking, strategic thinking, design thinking, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer de Bono’s dichotomy of thinking situations by basic types of focus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;area focus&lt;/strong&gt;, aimed to reveal new ideas ‘in this particular area’. This is totally free thinking without restrictions to thinking about problems, and goes beyond existing models, methods, and approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;purpose focus&lt;/strong&gt;, steered to solve the problem. It is grounded to a large extent on experience and concentrated on analysis, judgment, argument, and criticism. This is the more traditional thinking intended to achieve the desired result, to end up with a plan, to make an improvement in a defined direction, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A combination of diverse cognitive skills, which is varied through different intermediate states, is required to get a suitable outcome in both situation types. A unified, well-paved path from understanding the issue to choosing the optimal solution comprises the following basic steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-identification&quot;&gt;Problem identification&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the business world, most problem-solving situations are purpose-focused and are often ill-defined. The first step in turning spontaneous challenges into well-defined ones is the recognition of the discrepancy between what is the case and what should have been the case. This distinction is called a problem. Not all problems are equal. Some are clearly more important, while others are of greater urgency. The Eisenhower matrix is one of the prominent tools to facilitate prioritization, which helps to divide issues into four categories: do first, schedule for later, delegate, and skip. The difficulty of an issue is another differentiator and can be measured in many ways: whether the goal is achievable, the time required to find a solution, the quality of the solution, and so on. These measures are usually intertwined. In managing complex cases and under time pressure, there is a tendency to accept being ‘less wrong’ now rather than indefinitely pursue an ‘ideal’ solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An accurate problem identification allows one to prioritize, determine difficulty, and apply the right level of problem-solving to each situation. When people face an issue, it is necessary to recognize the problem environment — the space in which problem-solving activities take place. It includes information about what is desired, rules, different aspects of the initial situation, the target and its conditions, access to resources, various intermediate states (imagined or experienced), and any known or invented methods, concepts, and procedures to handle it. Clarifying the problem environment and setting a precise problem definition is the next step in making a challenge well-defined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem-definition&quot;&gt;Problem definition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem definition is the essential element of a problem space. It provides sense to an issue and destines its problem-solving. Asking the right questions is a key skill of a problem-solver that aims to unlock the details of a problem environment. Questions that help to think out a problem definition can be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When did the problem occur?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where did the problem occur?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What processes/ products/ services did the problem affect?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How is the problem measured?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the magnitude?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much does the problem cost in money, time, customer satisfaction, or another metric?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more specificly an issue is formulated, the better problem-solving outcome may be expected. To elaborate an accurate problem definition is far from obvious. Sometimes there are needs for decomposition to sub-problems, redefining a problem, or refocusing a purpose, which might result in a change of objectives. Different problem definitions usually lead to different solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a situation in which John—one of the most experienced developers — leaves a company on a short notice. If the problem is formulated with a very broad focus, like &lt;em&gt;‘how to prevent damage to a company’s business’&lt;/em&gt;, there is a danger to moving right out of the issue into some grand improvement in the business. In such a case, it makes sense to turn from a highly extensive purpose to a smaller and more specific one, like &lt;em&gt;‘how to replace John in the ongoing projects’; ‘how to retain John’; ‘how to prevent the turnover of other developers’&lt;/em&gt;, and so on. Obviously, these definitions do not tackle the same problem, require different problem-solving activities, and differing results should be accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also times to broaden the focus if the original one is too specific. For example, there is a challenge with overcoming stakeholders’ resistance to implementing a new filing system. Using the &lt;strong&gt;W5H&lt;/strong&gt; formula &lt;em&gt;(Who?, What?, Where?, When?, Why?, How?)&lt;/em&gt; that helps to extend the problem space, it might be discovered that the problem to solve has nothing to do with this filing system and requires a broader focus with a respective change of target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find a promising problem definition, it is necessary to be flexible in considering alternatives, consciously keep trying redefinitions in both directions to the workable level, and see how problem-solving might be carried out. The one to stick to depends on what the desired outcome, available resources, acceptable intermediate states, and other conditions of the problem space are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;options-consideration&quot;&gt;Options consideration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a problem sounds familiar, often the options consideration stage is skipped, and the preference is given to the best-guess approach. If a problem-solver is very familiar with an issue, granularly understands the problem environment, and has a rich knowledge base, (s)he might be able to get good results within the first few guesses. At the same time, extreme familiarity can cause a negative impact because a person might be ingrained with the traditional way of doing things. It may lead to missing minor, but essential differences in the problem space and a failure to make valuable best guesses. Even if the first guess regarding a solution yields a result that falls inside the parameters the problem-solver was looking for, it might be far away from the optimal one. Therefore, it makes sense to include examination of other feasible options in any problem-solving process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the problem is defined as &lt;em&gt;‘how to retain John’&lt;/em&gt;, one of the best-guesses could be to make a counteroffer and increase his salary. Assuming that a compensation issue was the only factor that triggered his decision (which in reality is a very rare case), with such a resolution the company may buy John’s loyalty for some period and get a set of risks associated with this option. A closer look at the problem environment may reveal other aspects to take into consideration. For example, pay attention to other factors that motivate or demotivate John, the last changes in his private situation, and so on. This data is a great source to generate a lot of ideas on how to retain him. Some of them hold the potential to be realized under some circumstances, but the rest will be eliminated as pure fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solution-selection&quot;&gt;Solution selection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each solution variant has some prerequisites to be implemented, as well as the accompanying risks that should be taken into account. Comparison of diverse parameters with the defined ones in the problem environment allows a problem-solver to shrink a number of feasible options to several alternatives, which are to be carefully analyzed. Diverse approaches to ranking, weighting, and other methods of analysis can be used to scrutinize and prioritize the selected alternatives. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-11-17-solution-selection.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
The result of these activities should be the optimal solution to the defined problem. Sometimes risks associated with the optimal choice might be higher than its potential benefit. Or an expected outcome of its implementation does not meet set requirements. In this case, there is a strong need to return to the problem definition phase and repeat it and the rest of the steps to come up with another solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This universal approach is applicable to any simple or complex issue. However, effective problem-solving assumes the fulfillment of each stage tailored to problem specifics. Some issues are the consequence of something going wrong and there is a need to find and fix the cause. Others require proactive preventive actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four types of problems, which may be classified into two sub-categories:
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/Smalley-problem-types.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;caused-problem-reactive-responses&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Caused problem/ Reactive responses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This set of issues appears as the result of a real cause that affected performance and the outcome deviated from the desired one. To grasp a problem under control and respond, some prompt actions are stand in need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 1—Trouble-shooting&lt;/strong&gt;. These are ‘firefighting’ cases that require immediate actions to reduce damage. If a beamer stops working during a customer presentation, you react to soften the audience’s inconvenience. If a fuse burns out in a test stand, the power must be unplugged. In case an issue requires follow-up activities to trace the cause, the rapid &lt;strong&gt;4Cs&lt;/strong&gt; problem-solving concept: &lt;em&gt;concern—cause—countermeasure—check results&lt;/em&gt; is applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 2—Gap from standard&lt;/strong&gt;. These are more severe or repetitive issues that hinder progress and often have a negative impact on the business. If the number of defective items produced on an assembly line is statistically higher than the set limit, there is a need to find and eliminate the root cause. If a noticeable share of projects ends up as a failure or with significant overuse of resources, there is a need to dig deep into processes to make corrections and fix causes. Spotting &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/RCA-qualitative-methods/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the root cause&lt;/a&gt; is a separate challenge and is usually solved by applying the 5-Why? technique, Ishikawa diagram, Failure Mode and Effect Analysis (FMEA), or [other instruments]/si/en/RCA-quantitative-methods/){:target=”_blank”}. For Type 2 issues, problem-solving might benefit from the &lt;strong&gt;DMAIC&lt;/strong&gt; approach: &lt;em&gt;define—measure—analyze—improve—control&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;created-problems-proactive-responses&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Created problems/ Proactive responses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This set is focused on continuous improvement and invention to tackle higher standards and create new opportunities. It generates actions in a constructed future-oriented problem environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 3—New target state&lt;/strong&gt;. The main driver of these problems is the pursuit of improvements over existing standards. Compared to the previous two types, the main idea here is not to fix, but rather to push the desired outcome to the next level and proactively create ‘how things should be’ requirements. There are plenty of triggers for a new target condition, like overtaking competitors, extending the customer base, boosting market penetration, advancing processes, and so on. Add-on functionalities in a working product to enhance its productivity and attractiveness for clients and programs aimed at improving customer experience are examples of Type 3 problems. To deal with such an issue, there is a necessity for advanced higher-order thinking skills to create a problem space, draft alternatives, and find an appropriate solution. The Deming cycle (&lt;strong&gt;PDCA&lt;/strong&gt;): &lt;em&gt;plan—do—check—act&lt;/em&gt; is the classical model to be based on for approaching continuous improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 4—Open-ended innovation&lt;/strong&gt;. Big innovation problems are entirely created and concentrated on the invention of completely new products, processes, or services. The first iPhone was an example of such a product. Focus on continuous improvement is required, but not enough to solve Type 4 issues. Besides that, creative and design thinking should be actively used that can be supported by the iterative &lt;strong&gt;DMADV&lt;/strong&gt; approach: &lt;em&gt;define — measure — analyze — design — verify&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving complex tasks is an iterative and repetitive process, where sometimes the optimal choice can only be seen in retrospect. In dealing with such situations, there is a need for a range of advanced thinking skills and solid methods to recognize issues and handle effective problem-solving processes. Conscious mental activities help to turn any ill-defined issue into a clear-cut one and favor finding relevant instruments focused on an appropriate solution. The above-presented models and techniques can serve as a base to start your journey in a problem-solving universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Allen Newell, Herbert A. Simon (1972). Human Problem Solving. ISBN: 13-445403-0&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Edward de Bono (1995). Teach Yourself to Think. ISBN: 978-0-2412-5750-0&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;John Aidar (1997). Decision Making and Problem Solving Strategies. ISBN: 978-0-7494-5551-4&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Art Smalley (2019). Four types of problems. ISBN: ‎978-1-9341-0955-7&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;University of Central Florida, Faculty Center. Bloom’s Taxonomy (https://fctl.ucf.edu/teaching-resources/course-design/blooms-taxonomy/)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Peak Performance Center. Types of Thinking (https://thepeakperformancecenter.com)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://svetlana-ilina.medium.com/effective-problem-solving-f005844d7efa&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on LinkedIn &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/universal-approach-problem-solving-svetlana-ilina-y1xgf/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Part1&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/types-problems-problem-solving-svetlana-ilina-rbclf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="problem-solving" /><category term="solution" /><category term="problem" /><category term="logic" /><category term="thinking" /><category term="root-cause" /><category term="method" /><summary type="html">“One should never impose one’s views on a problem; one should rather study it, and in time a solution will reveal itself.” Albert Einstein</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">An inability to reach an agreement: is it always a conflict?</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Abilene-paradox/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An inability to reach an agreement: is it always a conflict?" /><published>2023-10-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Abilene-paradox</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Abilene-paradox/">&lt;p&gt;Conflicts are part of any organization. Some of them have a destructive nature that ruins a productive working climate. Others are essential elements to synchronize different points of view during problem-solving that drive a team towards common targets. Usually several parties are involved in a conflict and it has a real cause or a set of causes that lie in various clusters: scarce resources, cost, priorities, processes, personal work styles, lack of competencies, missing or inappropriate ground rules, personality issues, etc. Ignoring or postponing conflict resolution with a real cause might lead to frustration, anger, and blooming faultfinding behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming behavior is a solid unhealthy symptom of a company and, often by default, it is assigned to the inability to manage conflict. However, it might result from the so-called &lt;strong&gt;Abilene paradox&lt;/strong&gt;, when there is no real conflict cause and involved people concur on the actions they want to take and then together do the opposite. Jerry B. Harvey says: &lt;em&gt;“Organizations frequently take actions in contradiction to what they really want to do and therefore defeat the very purposes they are trying to achieve.”&lt;/em&gt; It sounds absurd to some extent, but it happens more often than one could think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, I was a business partner of one industrial division that operated in a highly competitive market and had very demanding big clients. One day, a country account manager brought great news — the biggest local client wanted to replace its current automation system with the most modern and advanced one. The required technology was already piloting in the company in another country but on the local market, neither this division nor their competitors had ever undertaken such a project before. At the same time, this 7-figures project was considered a profitable one, and it also was seen as a door opener for a new market niche in the country. The division’s headquarters has agreed to support the local team. The country CEO was excited and pushy about this project because its implementation could advance the businesses of other divisions with this customer. The country division lead has already visualized how this project would strategically change the opportunity block for his business. The head of engineering looked forward to the acceleration of building up-to-date technical competencies and massive knowledge transfer to his department. The commercial division lead was satisfied with the planned project margin and checked that major risks had been considered. The project lead was motivated to take on this career-boosting challenge and actively participated in preparation for the tender. After a tough fight with competitors during the tender, the division won the project. The project plan was updated, monitoring systems were set, and the exciting journey began. After one year of execution, the project status became red. At the end of the second year, the company was fighting to reduce penalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the lessons learned session, it was discovered that key decision-makers who could influence the ‘no-go’ decision and stop this project did not share and properly articulate their concerns with others. The head of engineering discovered that the headquarters’ technical department had used a lot of contractors and subcontractors for the pilot and, in fact, had limited relevant in-house knowledge. So, knowledge acquisition became more complicated. He reported it as one of the risks but did not set the red flag for the project to start, because he saw how excited the rest were about the project. The division lead had a bad feeling about the project because the client was known as fault-finding and often changing an agreed work scope. However, he did not want his weird experience to damage opportunities, and believed in the professional mastery of the project manager and head of engineering, who seemed not to have strong doubts about the project’s success. Besides that, he could not report to the country CEO or HQ management gut feelings instead of confirmed facts. The commercial division lead was surprised that some risks were evaluated lower than she would expect, but as they were all from the technical side, she relied on estimates and mitigation actions suggested by the responsible colleagues. The project manager knew that the project would be complicated from technical and organizational points of view, with a real chance of failing because of diverse factors. He also saw an enormous inspiration about the project and support from all sides. So, he decided to do his best to be a good team player and focused on avoiding mistakes in project management processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the described situation, there was no real conflict cause, directly the opposite: all decision-makers wanted to support each other and to achieve the same target. On the individual level, each of them recognized a problem and knew how to cope with it. However, their inaccurate communication led to a misperception of the collective reality. This point was the fork in the road where the team went off the desired path and headed to Abilene. Then, with invalid information, members took collective decisions that started actions contrary to what they wanted to do, and arrived at the opposite results: instead of new lucrative business opportunities there were losses of money and to some extent competitive advantages and reputation. The paradoxical nature of this issue is &lt;strong&gt;the inability to manage agreement&lt;/strong&gt;: on the surface, it looks like team members have aligned their interests and agreed on actions to achieve a common target. But inside, their decision-making was based on misrepresented data and actually the team was far away from an agreement that its members indeed wanted to have.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/Abilene-paradox.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;120%&quot; style=&quot;float:center&quot; /&gt;
For a small or mid-sized company, such an Abilene trip can turn out to be the final destination of its business. For a big company with a stronger margin of business safety and bigger resources the situation might develop further and according to Harvey affects working productivity and well-being: &lt;em&gt;“As a result of taking actions that are counterproductive, organization members experience frustration, anger, irritation, and dissatisfaction with their organization. Frequently, they also blame authority figures and one another.”&lt;/em&gt; If the paradox is not recognized and appropriate corrective actions are not taken, most probably it ends in Abilene and then will repeat itself with greater intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of reasons why team members are not able to manage an agreement. One of them is the fear of being tabbed as a “non-team player”. The dominant trend in organizational development focusing strongly on teamwork and positive thinking besides the obviously positive side that ensures the development of breakthrough technologies and businesses might serve as a greenhouse of an individual’s fear of being one who spoils a team’s common inspiration and excitement. Another reason is deeply rooted in the dimension of corporate culture, when disagreement could be considered as ‘disloyalty’ and no one wants to be a messenger that brings bad news. The list of grounds can be extended to various aspects of psychology, human perceptions, individual values, motivation, and group dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paradox can be revealed on the way or post factum. Anyway, a search for the culprits is not the right action to take. It is counterproductive and diverts a team from problem-solving required to redirect a company along the route it really wants to take. Attempts to eliminate the paradox by applying standard methods of conflict resolution are doomed to fail, because any Abilene trip is the inability to manage agreement, not the inability to manage a conflict. The power to destroy the paradox comes from speaking to the underlying reality of the situation. Therefore, accurate messaging and a corporate culture that favors fearless and open communication are the keys to being able to manage agreements really beneficial for a company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/inability-reach-agreement-always-conflict-svetlana-ilina%3FtrackingId=FbqTnKq37JURbGb2yI9NYQ%253D%253D/?trackingId=FbqTnKq37JURbGb2yI9NYQ%3D%3D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="case-study" /><category term="communication" /><category term="conflict" /><category term="culture" /><category term="fallacy" /><category term="paradox" /><category term="team" /><summary type="html">Conflicts are part of any organization. Some of them have a destructive nature that ruins a productive working climate. Others are essential elements to synchronize different points of view during problem-solving that drive a team towards common targets. Usually several parties are involved in a conflict and it has a real cause or a set of causes that lie in various clusters: scarce resources, cost, priorities, processes, personal work styles, lack of competencies, missing or inappropriate ground rules, personality issues, etc. Ignoring or postponing conflict resolution with a real cause might lead to frustration, anger, and blooming faultfinding behavior.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">22 Common Errors in Reasoning</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/logical-fallacies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="22 Common Errors in Reasoning" /><published>2023-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/logical-fallacies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/logical-fallacies/">&lt;p&gt;Efficient communication is a cornerstone of any successful project, and arguments and debates are an important part of it. Each good communication should have a call to action. In order to achieve it, the affected groups of people must experience all the stages of the commitment curve: preparation (contact, awareness), acceptance (understanding, positive perception), and commitment.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/Conner-commitment-curve.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
Logic is a powerful tool for persuading an audience by providing valid argumentation and reasonable statements in the course of the communication process. However, not every argument or statement is solid. Some might have errors in reasoning and rhetoric and lead to incorrect conclusions. These are so-called “logical fallacies”. They indicate either illegitimate arguments or irrelevant points, and often can be identified because they lack evidence that supports their statement. They can be used intentionally to manipulate or trick an audience or can be made unwittingly by mistake. Fallacies have a lot of variations and may be present in all forms of human communication. Often they are classified by errors in the structure (a formal fallacy), and errors in the form, content, or context of the argument (an informal fallacy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;does-not-follow-non-sequitur&quot;&gt;“Does not follow” &lt;em&gt;(non sequitur)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All &lt;strong&gt;formal fallacies&lt;/strong&gt; are associated with &lt;em&gt;non sequitur&lt;/em&gt; error types where reasoning goes wrong, i.e. a presented conclusion is not necessarily a logical result of the given facts. Reaching logical conclusions depends on the proper analysis of statements taken to be true and used as a basis for reasoning, so-called premises. In order to work, logic requires decisive statements based on reliable and complete facts accepted by the audience. It also leans on which factors are recognized and ignored by the premises. Therefore, premises that are correct but ignore other essential information might drive misleading conclusions.
Some examples of formal fallacies are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In 2020 the average market salary of IT specialists has noticeably increased, therefore the qualification of IT staff hired in that year must be very high.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Developers wear comfortable hoodies and jeans. Peter comes to the first interview in a business suit, therefore he is not a developer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some high performers have the potential for further development and belong to a company’s top talent group. After a performance review, Marie was evaluated as a high performer, therefore, she is a top talent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The landscape of &lt;strong&gt;informal fallacies&lt;/strong&gt; has a vast variety and can be categorized in different ways. Among others, it might be a lack of relevance, present improper presumptions, faulty generalizations, and errors in assigning causation. Some of these fallacies are known since the first public speeches in Ancient times, others have appeared and bloomed together with the development of advertising, marketing, political technologies, social media, and the business environment. Sitting in a business meeting, surfing the Internet, or going to a shopping mall, we can observe plenty of logically unsound premises and based on them false conclusions, like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;appeal-to-authority-argumentum-ad-auctoritate&quot;&gt;Appeal to authority &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad auctoritate)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a misusage of an authority’s opinion. A statement made by an authority on some topic is used as evidence to support one’s argument disregarding circumstances such as the reliability and relevance of the information to the issue, the existence of a widespread agreement among authorities, or alternative opinions on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;To be competitive, our company has to speed up the implementation of modern technologies and agile approaches. Jeff Sutherland states that the SCRUM framework can be used in any business, therefore we must apply this method to all our construction projects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;appeal-to-emotions&quot;&gt;Appeal to emotions&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a set of fallacies provoking emotions (fear, flattery, pity, ridicule, etc.) to win a statement or a debate. These fallacies attempt to pull on an audience’s emotions, manipulate, and distract listeners instead of using valid reasoning to obtain an agreement. For instance, the &lt;strong&gt;appeal to pity&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad misericordiam)&lt;/em&gt; aims to generate feelings of sympathy or mercy, or the &lt;strong&gt;appeal to ridicule&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;(reductio ad ridiculum, ad absurdum)&lt;/em&gt; is a diversion from the merits of the opponent’s arguments by mocking or stating that an opponent’s position is laughable or absurd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;During annual performance reviews, such a speech of a line manager excusing the underperformance of an employee is not a rare case: “Lora is a nice young lady. This year was very difficult for her: she lost her grandmother and has permanent problems with her boyfriend. That is why she is sometimes rude to clients, quarrels with colleagues, and has missed several important deadlines. If we assign her to the ‘need improvements’ category, it will be an additional stress for her.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;appeal-to-hypocrisy-you-too-tu-quoque&quot;&gt;Appeal to hypocrisy/ “you too” &lt;em&gt;(tu quoque)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fallacy deflects criticism away from oneself by accusing the other person of the same problem or something comparable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are not in a position to criticize the retention methods of my department while the fluctuation rate of your department is also higher than the targeted one.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;appeal-to-ignorance-argumentum-ad-ignorantiam&quot;&gt;Appeal to ignorance &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad ignorantiam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is based on the speculation that a proposition must be true because it has not been proven false or vice versa. The fallacy allows shifting the need for proof of a statement away from the person making a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;We have no evidence that this risk has ever been realized in our projects, so it has to be excluded from risk analysis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bandwagon-appeal-argument-to-people-argumentum-ad-populum&quot;&gt;Bandwagon appeal/ Argument to people &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad populum)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It assumes that something is true or right because others think it is so. The fallacy is an attempt to influence one to think the same way as the multitude (most people or a group of people) does. It appeals to emotions and the feeling of togetherness rather than facts and evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A genuine patriot of our company always goes the extra mile and never complains about overtime.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;begging-the-question-petitio-principii&quot;&gt;Begging the Question &lt;em&gt;(petitio principii)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A statement that should be validated is presented as truth and misled to assume something has been proved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overwhelmed and ineffective modernization should be stopped.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;circular-reasoning-circulus-in-probando&quot;&gt;Circular reasoning &lt;em&gt;(circulus in probando)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a restatement of the same argument rather than actually proving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our manager is an excellent communicator because he speaks effectively.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;changing-the-subject-red-herring&quot;&gt;Changing the subject/ Red herring&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the common tactics that diverts attention from the main issue by introducing irrelevant points intended to replace the lack of real arguments or to replace implicitly the subject of the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our team lead wants to talk about my morning lateness, so I asked her what she is going to do with delays in customers’ payments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;cherry-picking-card-stacking-fallacy-of-incomplete-evidence&quot;&gt;Cherry-picking/ Card-stacking/ Fallacy of incomplete evidence&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens by carefully selecting facts and evidences to confirm a particular position and skipping or ignoring data that may contradict this position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Presentation of achievements:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-06-12-card-stacking.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;genetic-fallacy-fallacy-of-origins-fallacy-of-virtue&quot;&gt;Genetic fallacy/ Fallacy of origins/ Fallacy of virtue&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fallacy assumes that information or arguments are validated based on their source of origin (a person, group, organizational unit, or institute) rather than their content. The focus shifts from ‘what’ and ‘why’ have been said to ‘who’ said it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The objections to the new target-setting process come only from the R&amp;amp;D department and can be ignored.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;false-cause-post-hoc-ergo-propter-hoc&quot;&gt;False cause &lt;em&gt;(post hoc ergo propter hoc)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens when a conclusion is solely based on the order of events and other factors potentially responsible for the outcome are not considered. In other words, a temporal sequence implies causation: if ‘A’ occurred after ‘B’, then ‘B’ must have caused ‘A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;We should not arrange an open-air company party because every time we do, heavy rain comes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;false-comparison-faulty-analogy-comparing-apples-and-oranges&quot;&gt;False comparison/ Faulty analogy/ &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Comparing apples and oranges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It assumes that if two things are similar in one or several aspects, they are necessarily identical in some others or all the rest facets. Often, a similarity might be based on ignorance of additional factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;This product development project has the same estimated duration as one of our infrastructure projects, therefore it requires a similar budget.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;false-compromise-argument-to-moderation-middle-ground-fallacy-of-the-golden-mean-argumentum-ad-temperantiam&quot;&gt;False compromise/ Argument to moderation/ Middle ground/ Fallacy of the golden mean &lt;em&gt;(argumentum ad temperantiam)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It assumes that a compromise between two opposite positions is always correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subject matter experts estimate a project duration of one year, but the customer wants its completion in 4 months, therefore a sales manager has prepared a contract with an 8-month project duration without corrections in the project scope, output, and budget.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;false-dilemma-false-dichotomy-either--or-black-or-white&quot;&gt;False dilemma/ False dichotomy/ Either – or/ Black or white&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fallacy reduces the options of a complex issue to two extremes: often one right, one wrong. This is a manipulative tool aimed to promote one side and exaggerate the negative effects of another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Internship students come to a company to work hard or to loaf.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A company has either to invest in A, B, and C technologies to become the market leader or sell its business.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;hasty-generalization-fallacy-of-insufficient-sample&quot;&gt;Hasty generalization/ Fallacy of insufficient sample&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens when reasoning is based on insufficient or biased evidence. Often, this fallacy can be met in presentations of survey results when conclusions are derived from a small sample group that does not sufficiently represent an entire population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Despite good grades during his study, the intern does a lot of mistakes in working tasks. Therefore, our department won’t accept interns who graduated from this university anymore.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-08-12-pulse-response-rate.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The results of &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/pulse-check/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the pulse-check 202X&lt;/a&gt; show that in our company employees are very satisfied with their line managers. The average satisfaction value is 76,75.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;irrelevant-conclusion-missing-the-point-ignoratio-elenchi&quot;&gt;Irrelevant conclusion/ Missing the point &lt;em&gt;(ignoratio elenchi)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens when provided arguments may be valid, but do not address or relate to the issue in the discussed question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;John is clearly an experienced manager. He has a warm family life and regularly takes part in volunteer projects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;personal-attack-ad-hominem&quot;&gt;Personal attack &lt;em&gt;(ad hominem)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an attack on the character of a person rather than a debate about her opinions or arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is a waste of time to discuss the claims of the procurement department about the project organization because they are all foolish quibblers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;slippery-slope&quot;&gt;Slippery slope&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It supposes that if a certain event occurs, it will necessarily lead to a chain of small steps or future events ending in a predefined result. The starting point is equated to the outcome. In other words, if we do not want this result to occur, the initial event must be prevented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;If psychometrics is not used in an assessment center (AC), AC results will not be valid.&lt;/em&gt; 
(Psychometrics is reliable and suitable for some situations instrument. However, the design of an assessment center is a complex task with multiple facets that affected its validity.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;straw-man&quot;&gt;Straw Man&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an oversimplification of an opponent’s viewpoint and then attacks a different subject rather than the topic being discussed. The purpose of this misdirection is to make one’s position look stronger than it actually is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Division leads who don’t support a continuous increase of the company’s well-being budget hate our employees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;sunk-cost&quot;&gt;Sunk cost&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fallacy describes the tendency to follow through on an endeavor if time, effort, or money have been already invested into it, regardless of whether the additional costs outweigh the potential benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;We have invested $ xxx into a HRM system, but it does not fit our internal processes and the results of its implementation are far away from the planned ones. The system provider offers customization, it will cost in the range of the initial investment or slightly more. Considering already spent money, time, and effort, it makes sense to customize the system.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;testimonial-anecdotal-evidence&quot;&gt;Testimonial/ Anecdotal evidence&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happens when a statement is made only based on personal observation, collected in a casual manner. Intentionally this fallacy is used in advertising when a respected or well-known person promotes something in an area where they lack expert knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A famous artist recommends a bank.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The chief accountant recommends to the chief engineer how to set up a production line.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Spotting weak points in arguments is a gained habit. It can and should be trained to be applied in communication activities. It is helpful to notice mistakes in reasoning being in a receiver position to separate the grain from the chaff. And it is even more important to check your own messages on fallacies to avoid transmitting misleading information. Logical reasoning is one of the most powerful convincing methods, however, to strengthen communication efficiency it is worth addressing the values and emotions of people besides arguments. Therefore, experienced influencers are using a diverse spectrum of instruments and methods to work with and persuade their audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/22-common-errors-reasoning-svetlana-ilina/?trackingId=oYspSlnyTtydt6C1YM1oDw%3D%3D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="communication" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="logic" /><category term="fallacy" /><category term="pitfall" /><summary type="html">Efficient communication is a cornerstone of any successful project, and arguments and debates are an important part of it. Each good communication should have a call to action. In order to achieve it, the affected groups of people must experience all the stages of the commitment curve: preparation (contact, awareness), acceptance (understanding, positive perception), and commitment. Logic is a powerful tool for persuading an audience by providing valid argumentation and reasonable statements in the course of the communication process. However, not every argument or statement is solid. Some might have errors in reasoning and rhetoric and lead to incorrect conclusions. These are so-called “logical fallacies”. They indicate either illegitimate arguments or irrelevant points, and often can be identified because they lack evidence that supports their statement. They can be used intentionally to manipulate or trick an audience or can be made unwittingly by mistake. Fallacies have a lot of variations and may be present in all forms of human communication. Often they are classified by errors in the structure (a formal fallacy), and errors in the form, content, or context of the argument (an informal fallacy).</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Critical Issues and Success Factors in HR projects: Processes</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Processes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Critical Issues and Success Factors in HR projects: Processes" /><published>2023-04-21T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-04-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Processes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Processes/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“If you can’t fly, then run. If you can’t run, then walk. If you can’t walk, then crawl. But whatever you do, you have to keep moving forward.”&lt;/em&gt;  Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within recent decades business environment has been described as &lt;em&gt;volatile, uncertain, complex, and ambiguous&lt;/em&gt; (VUCA), and companies had to shape their strategies and elaborate approaches to navigate through frequent, rapid, and sometimes confusing trends and changes in technology, social, and business culture. Drastic economical, political, technological, social, and climate challenges of the last years sharpen the chaotic component of the world and push businesses to deal with a &lt;em&gt;brittle, anxious, nonlinear, and incomprehensible&lt;/em&gt; (BANI) environment. It dictates and drives immediate business responses to catch new opportunities and adjust a company’s strategy and objectives to secure its vitality. These changes speed up HR transformation and require HR-function to become more analytical, more agile, more digital, and more competent in handling different programs and initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, transformative HR initiatives and programs comprise diverse &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/PM-HR_strangers-or-buddies/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HR projects&lt;/a&gt; endeavoring to support the achievements of specific business objectives, to deliver value-add, and to reorganize, automate, and improve processes. As with any project, they are time-boxed and aimed at delivering results. Despite significant diversity in purpose, &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complexity&lt;/a&gt;, duration, available resources, budget, risks, and other constraints, there are some &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Hindrances-in-HRprojects/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;common critical issues&lt;/a&gt; to keep an eye on in any HR project. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/critical-issues-hr-projects.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
Handling these fulcrums — &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholders&lt;/a&gt;, processes, culture, and competencies — directly redound in project success or failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processes belong to and ensure the core functionalities of HR. Process management in the context of HR projects has several aspects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the interconnection of processes across different HR areas, compound to a common system, and leverage points;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the conjunction of HR processes with a business process system;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;processes and approaches to drive and handle HR initiatives, programs, and projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interconnection-of-hr-processes-and-leverage-points&quot;&gt;Interconnection of HR processes and leverage points&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HR is made up of complex, intertwined processes and systems, which are highly integrated into and influenced by a company’s culture, strategy, and operational business objectives. Often &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Maturity-of-processes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the maturity of HR processes&lt;/a&gt; reflects the attitude and approaches to the organization of processes in a company or trails a step behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HR projects touch and in most cases directly concentrate on processes. An HR process is a collection of tasks, steps, or activities that are performed, usually in a specific order, and result in a provision of services. Multiple processes in different HR areas are interwoven, often organized in systems, and work together to achieve the same goal or goals. To get a reliable system processes should be as simple as possible, consistent, and documented. There is no need for long eloquent process descriptions, but a process map is very helpful to monitor duplications, missing and “grey” zones, and leverage points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An effective working system has good vitality in tolerating accidental errors and manageable interventions. At the same time, any system has critical places where intentional actions can create a ripple effect that leads to lasting positive or negative change. Identifying such leverage points is a tricky task. It should be done by subject matter experts, who are familiar with the system’s features and understand how changes might impact inputs and outcomes of processes on a granular level. Because of the complexity and interconnectedness of HR processes, intentional, but crude or low-controlled interventions damage their stability and efficiency, which has an outsized impact on the functioning of the system as a whole. To avoid it, a regular audit of processes should be done to ensure system sustainability, adaptability, and efforts- and cost-effectiveness of the existing processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, an HR project started as a response to a strategic business initiative serves as a great impetus to the revision of HR processes and systems. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2021/2021-06-23.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
For example, an HR project aimed at supporting rapid business growth won’t be limited to one HR area and its processes, even if at the beginning only recruitment targets are set. After a kick-off meeting, it will be clear that the targets’ accomplishment requires a lot of supportive actions and sub-projects in adjacent areas. One of &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/PM-and-HRtransformation/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;my headcount ramp-up projects&lt;/a&gt; ended up in the revision of the whole HR system, designing new and adjusting some existing processes in different HR areas, establishing a lot of conjunctions with business processes, and influencing on development of the corporate culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conjunction-with-a-business-process-system&quot;&gt;Conjunction with a business process system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An assessment of the influence of changes on internal HR processes and systems is to be an initial step in any HR project. It has to be done proactively and cover the complete range of processes in the directly affected and coterminous zones. Besides that, adjoining processes in other functional areas should also be considered. For example, those who survived an ERP migration most probably can recall a lot of complaints from a controlling department about strange data appearing in their reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In immature companies, a generally chaotic organization of processes often disguises the real impact of HR processes on other functions and their business processes, which might lead to an underestimation of their interconnectivity and sway on business results. On the contrary, in companies with a mature organization of processes, the system might be extremely complicated and bureaucratic to allow all-around assessments. In both cases, HR professionals have to deal with comprehensive and go-ahead estimations of internal HR and cross-functional interdependencies to prevent an increasing number of blocking stakeholders, growing project complexity, and deteriorating the quality of a project outcome. Unfortunately, such estimations are not always a strong suit in HR projects, which leads to a permanent search for workaround solutions to close emerging gaps. That spawns low-controlled overlapping and duplications of processes, fosters excrescent deleterious “a process for a process”-elements, and damages a system’s integrity, consistency, transparency, and stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;handling-hr-initiatives-programs-and-projects&quot;&gt;Handling HR initiatives, programs, and projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drastic changes in reaction speed and agility of HR-function to meet requirements of business transformation result in a focus on project work. However, the principles of project management are underestimated or, to some extent, ignored in HR world. That might cause compelled rework, overrun budget and time, or overall outcome failure. As with any project, HR initiative or program should follow the common &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Five-steps/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;process of project management&lt;/a&gt; and, if necessary, tune its phases to corporate, legal, and regional requirements. A typical process of managing HR projects usually sequences two core stages embracing important phases.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-04-21-phases-hr-projects.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;170%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial project stage is &lt;em&gt;a compass&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. it sets a general project direction and its frames. It starts with clarification and &lt;strong&gt;analysis of needs&lt;/strong&gt;. During this phase, plausible ideas are collected, analyzed, and clarified with a project sponsor. A vision of the outcome, requirements, and involved parties are typical results of this phase. It is followed by &lt;strong&gt;high-level estimates&lt;/strong&gt; of benefits, risks, complexity, amount of work, costs, resources, and schedule. Depending on project specifics, other constraints can be also assessed. This phase is a basis for preparing decisions about the project realization, refining the list of requirements, allocation of resources, and budget assignment. Skipping any of the basic estimates or the whole phase guarantees a bulk of unpleasant surprises during the project execution. The &lt;strong&gt;approval&lt;/strong&gt; phase completes the initial stage. During this process step, decisions about the project execution are taken, targets and acceptance criteria are set, and budget, time, and key resources are confirmed. A frivolous attitude to the importance of the initial stage puts in pledge enormous pressure on a project team during the execution stage and jeopardizes the success of a not yet-started project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;clarification&lt;/strong&gt; commences the execution stage and focuses on project objectives, scope, prioritization of tasks, stakeholders, available resources (people, time, money), risks, and constraints. Best practices assume that an appointed project manager arranges a project kick-off meeting to discuss these issues and agrees upon the project organization and execution with a sponsor, subject matter experts, a project team, and key decision makers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the &lt;strong&gt;planning&lt;/strong&gt; phase, a project plan including technical and functional specifications, risks analysis, time and cost forecasts, work breakdown structure, time schedule with milestones, and a communication strategy should be developed. An excessively detailed and rigid plan as well as the opposite—an extremely sketchy plan does not provide the required guidance and support during the implementation. The detailing should be suitable to make founded decisions and see trees without losing the picture of the entire forest. The results of clarification and planning phases serve as &lt;em&gt;a map&lt;/em&gt; with drafted trails through the project to achieve its targets and objectives. Starting an implementation journey, it is vital to have both a compass and a map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the common mistakes in handling HR projects is a lack of searching for optimal leverage points in HR processes and systems or postponing it from the planning to the implementation phase. Another critical issue that should be taken into account during the planning phase is solving the dilemmas: keeping a functional simplicity vs. ignorance of a bounded complexity and moving beyond an acceptable level of complexity vs. unreasonable simplification. The thoughtful planning provides a comprehensive overview of the project landscape and allows rational navigation between alternatives, mitigation of potential risks, optimal allocation of resources, and overall uncertainty reduction that increase the chances of successful project completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;implementation&lt;/strong&gt; is the most visible, dynamic, and time-consuming project phase. Rollout under permanent monitoring, controlling, and supervision of work progress are the principal components of this phase. At the same time, it highlights defects in handling HR projects done in the previous process steps. Some of them can be patched with a slight variation of the project outcome. Others might lead to the growing &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Onion-syndrome/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;onion syndrome in a project&lt;/a&gt;, a sizable run-over budget, a significant increase in time, or project failure. Having a compass and a well-done map allows a project team confidently to solve and maneuver between the different pop-up problems during the implementation and overcome emerging challenges of the BANI environment. In the pursuit of agility, one of the frequent pitfalls during this phase is the launching of many simultaneous changes in various HR processes and systems without their proper piloting or at least revisiting the planning phase. That often creates chaos in a project and complicates its handling and the achievement of the set targets and objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The execution stage is completed by obtaining acceptance of project results, archiving project documentation, releasing project resources and infrastructure, and analyzing the achieved outcome. Retrospectives are the most important component of the &lt;strong&gt;closure&lt;/strong&gt; phase that focuses on lessons learned and room for improvements in processes, organization, and handling of HR projects. That elaborates a valuable basis for the successful realization of further HR initiatives and programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prosperous launch of transformative HR programs is a challenging task that requires a deep understanding of process management and expert subject knowledge. Despite the functional specifics, any HR initiative is just one of the possible types of projects to which standard project management methodology and approaches should be applied. It helps to avoid a lot of traps in handling HR projects, prevents realization derailment, and accelerates the transition of the HR function to the new partnering level with the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Josh Bersin Company. HR Predictions for 2023. www.joshbersin.com&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jeff Sutherland (2014). SCRUM: The Art of Doing Twice the Work in Half the Time. ISBN: 9781847941107&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tom DeMarco (2002). Slack: getting past burnout, busywork, and the myth of total efficiency. ISBN: 0-7679-0769-8&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Donella H. Meadows (1999). Leverage Points: Places to Intervene in a System. The Sustainability Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jamais Cascio (2020). Facing the Age of Chaos. www.medium.com&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Project Management Institute (2017, 2021). 
&lt;em&gt;A Guide to the Project Management Body of Knowledge (PMBOK® Guide).&lt;/em&gt; Sixth and Seventh Editions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Axelos. (2017). 
&lt;em&gt;Managing Successful Projects with PRINCE2®.&lt;/em&gt; Sixth Edition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://svetlana-ilina.medium.com/critical-issues-and-success-factors-in-hr-projects-processes-65302332368f&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on LinkedIn &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/critical-issues-success-factors-hr-projects-processes-svetlana-ilina-hurqc/?trackingId=9tUFSJVW72T5Mm5Iqjy5vg%3D%3D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/navigation-toolset-hr-transformation-scouts-svetlana-ilina-5ji1f/?trackingId=IbaiBpM6RVWeqE5mvFAVUQ%3D%3D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="BANI" /><category term="VUCA" /><category term="hr-project" /><category term="processes" /><category term="risk" /><category term="success-factor" /><category term="project-management" /><category term="pitfall" /><category term="initiation" /><category term="execution" /><summary type="html">“If you can’t fly, then run. If you can’t run, then walk. If you can’t walk, then crawl. But whatever you do, you have to keep moving forward.” Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Transformation of HR Processes:from chaos to ecosystem</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Maturity-of-processes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transformation of HR Processes:from chaos to ecosystem" /><published>2023-02-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-02-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Maturity-of-processes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Maturity-of-processes/">&lt;p&gt;According to Wikipedia, a process &lt;em&gt;“is a series or set of activities that interact to produce a result; it may occur once-only or be recurrent or periodic“&lt;/em&gt;. These activities are to be decomposed into some number of steps, sequenced in a specific order, and performed for a purpose. In a business, multiple processes work together to achieve a company’s goals. Processes are the carcass of any complex organization. They serve to reduce chaos  and provide systematic approaches, methods, practices, and procedures to deal with both repetitive and unique tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Process maturity is the extent to which a specific process is explicitly defined, managed, measured, controlled, and effective. One of the most commonly used process maturity frameworks derives from the software development area, where the quality of processes has an immediately visible effect on business results. It is a part of the Capability Maturity Model for Software (CMM). The framework comprises five levels:
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/5steps-processes-maturity.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Initial&lt;/em&gt;: The process is characterized as ad hoc, and occasionally even chaotic. Few processes are defined, and success depends on individual efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Repeatable&lt;/em&gt;: Basic processes are established. Some processes are repeatable, possibly with consistent results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defined&lt;/em&gt;: There are sets of defined and documented standard processes established and subject to some degree of improvement over time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Managed&lt;/em&gt;: Detailed measures of the process and outcome quality are collected and controlled.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Optimizing&lt;/em&gt;: Continuous process improvement is enabled by quantitative feedback from the process and from piloting innovative ideas and technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The maturity of processes’ organization indicates both the richness of a company’s processes and the consistency with which it is applied in an enterprise. At a given time, different processes can be assigned to diverse maturity levels that affect the overall level of an organization of processes. With an immature organization, most processes are improvised by practitioners and even specified ones are not rigorously followed or enforced. With a mature organization, processes are accurately communicated to executors and other &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholders&lt;/a&gt;, work activities are carried out according to the planned processes, and the quality of outcome and customer satisfaction is monitored, controlled, and continuously improved. The more mature an organization of processes is better an objective, quantitative basis for judging quality and analyzing problems with outcomes and processes themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting from some degree of organizational development, processes tend to be integrated, interconnected, and organized into a common system. As a company matures, its processes become better defined within and across different business areas and more consistently implemented throughout the organization. HR is made up of complex, intertwined processes and systems, which are highly integrated into and influenced by a company’s culture, strategy, and operational business objectives. Often the maturity of HR processes reflects the attitude and the way the organization of processes in a company or trails a little bit behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reinvent-the-wheel&quot;&gt;Reinvent the wheel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the starting stage where any task is titled as a strategic challenge requiring an elaboration of a unique solution. This is a typical situation for startups and unfortunately not a rare case for mid-sized companies. The key characteristics of the HR function at this stage are a lack of systematic approach, chaotic organization of work, unpredictable outcomes for similar tasks, and high dependence of results on individual efforts. These might foster a forming of counterproductive working habits, which hamper the movement to the next organizational level and a significant resistance of executors to changes. The immature HR organization is reactionary, and practitioners are usually focused on solving immediate crises. A prolonged jamming at this stage prevents HR from being considered a reliable partner and a value-add for the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first transformative step from the chaos is to identify &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/PMandTasks/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;administrative, operational, tactical, and strategic HR tasks&lt;/a&gt; and classify them in terms of repetitiveness, for example, frequent, rare, and unique. In an immature organization, a portfolio of HR services is very limited and most probably bounded by the basics of administrative and operational tasks. For frequent administrative and operational working tasks, appropriate processes and clear procedures should be designed. A high task recurrence allows practitioners to test and quickly tune processes to be effective. Because of the relative simplicity of tasks, these processes are to be simple, transparent, with clear input and output data, and well-defined and documented sets of required sequential steps. To maximize the effect, these processes are to be coherent to arrange them into simple working systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the essential hindrances at this stage is the capability of HR practitioners, who dealt with truncated HR processes only, to design appropriate consistent processes for different HR areas. A shortcut solution in this situation can be the adoption of processes embedded into one of HRTech solutions offered by software providers. Another option is to invite an external consultant or a process manager from a business to help HR practitioners set up steady and scalable processes. Besides the capability of processes’ design and implementation, supportive change management activities have to be undertaken to ensure smooth and efficient transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;replicate-results&quot;&gt;Replicate results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the next stage of the organization of HR processes on the maturity journey. The main characteristics of the HR function at this level are defined processes for most repetitive tasks, minor deviation of results for similar activities, low dependence on specifics of executors, a set of independent systems and processes with a partial overlapping and the necessity of manual input or Excel-based data exchange between them. Because of the stable delivery of acceptable outcomes for the majority of administrative and operational tasks, HR is a respected function for the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of companies are stuck at this level polishing instead of improving processes and maintaining instead of optimizing a lot of outdated systems. To move forward, HR organization is to focus on bundling independent systems into complex ones to reduce partial duplication of processes and decrease the number of mistakes caused by significant manual data handling. Many processes are to be automated. On the market, there are plenty of HRTech solutions to be selected from and to fit the specific requirements of a company to functionality, set of HR processes, and degree of customization. Such a solution can be embedded into the company’s system of HR processes or the internal organization of HR processes can be adjusted to the solution’s requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-02-28-tasks-levels-frequency.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
Digitalization of HR processes to support the employee lifecycle and a positive employee experience requires significant change management activities to get the acceptance and commitment of all affected stakeholders. To solve such a task, HR practitioners have to know the basics of project management and be capable of applying it in practice. This is another area of improvement. The application of project management to deal with tactical and strategic tasks facilitates HR to become more flexible, proactive, and strategic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;continuous-improvement&quot;&gt;Continuous improvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the advanced stage. The main characteristics of the mature HR function are high automation with the necessary infrastructure to support it, a system of HR processes that ensures managed processes and predictable results for repetitive tasks, a confident handling of unique challenges, a strong focus on the quality of outcome, and integration with some business processes. Roles and responsibilities within the defined processes are clear across the HR and other affected functions. HR organization is a valuable asset for a company and a reliable partner for the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any process is going to have variations. The normal variation within a process is caused by the process itself (for example, typing errors by HR admins). If the output of one process serves as an input for another process, deliberate tracking, control, and management of normal variations open a great reserve for refinements. Continuous process improvement is based on many small, evolutionary steps rather than revolutionary innovations. It should focus on the needs of the HR function in the context of its business environment. Besides cost-effectiveness, agility, and adaptability to business needs, transparency, consistency, predictability, and plainness are core requirements of HR processes and systems. To get better results, efforts should be placed on enhancing the quality of input and output data, optimization of process steps and procedures, shrinking and aligning variations, and tighter integration of HR processes into one common system. The transformative step at this stage is an evolutional move to the HR ecosystem covering all HR-related areas, deeply embedded into a complex business processes system of a company, and embraced by the required project management and culture change activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ecosystem of HR processes is the desired transformative objective. A lot of companies set this transformation as the immediate HR target, ignoring the actual maturity degree of the organization. The ability to implement processes from higher maturity levels does not imply that some levels can be skipped, because each forms a necessary foundation from which to achieve the next stage. HR processes are dedicated to driving job satisfaction, engagement, and productivity of employees, providing a ground for the HR business partnering, shaping the corporate culture, and supporting business in the achieving its strategic goals. In other words, they serve the needs of people and the business. Therefore, the maturity of the organization of HR processes is tightly linked and should be balanced with the maturity level of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/transformation-hr-processes-from-chaos-ecosystem-svetlana-ilina/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="digitalisation" /><category term="hr-transformation" /><category term="processes" /><summary type="html">According to Wikipedia, a process “is a series or set of activities that interact to produce a result; it may occur once-only or be recurrent or periodic“. These activities are to be decomposed into some number of steps, sequenced in a specific order, and performed for a purpose. In a business, multiple processes work together to achieve a company’s goals. Processes are the carcass of any complex organization. They serve to reduce chaos and provide systematic approaches, methods, practices, and procedures to deal with both repetitive and unique tasks.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The “onion syndrome” in projects:7 practical tips to nip it in the bud</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Onion-syndrome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The “onion syndrome” in projects:7 practical tips to nip it in the bud" /><published>2023-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Onion-syndrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Onion-syndrome/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The art of life is a constant readjustment to our surroundings.”&lt;/em&gt;  Okakura Kakuzo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine or recall a case when an additional project pops up in your work. A brief screening shows that probably it won’t be too complicated despite a lot of minor differences from what you have done before. Your working schedule is full of other important or urgent tasks and you simply do not have time for long cogitation and analysis. You ideate how the outcome might look like and know that deviations are natural, unavoidable, and usually they can be fixed during project execution. Raw estimates of the proposed budget and deadlines sound fair, project work looks more or less clear and not scary, ergo you are ready to start your straight path to the project’s success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murphy’s law says: &lt;em&gt;“anything that can go wrong will go wrong”&lt;/em&gt; and suddenly your project illustrates it. In the beginning, there are light signs of potential complications (add-on features or requirements, new stakeholders, another set of deliverables, etc.) that you might not notice or ignore to keep on moving ahead. After some time, you face an issue and might skip or postpone it instead of fixing it. You continue to move forward, ignoring or underestimating consequences. Then another complication pops up and another one, and then some more. Problems are growing like a snowball. The project becomes hardly controlled and its complexity unexpectedly runs to the sky. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/onion-syndrome.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
To patch and fix the appeared troubles, the amount of project work swells, the project duration lengthens, and the project path takes the shape of a bulb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this situation sounds familiar to you, you have already experienced the ‘onion syndrome’, where a bulb size depends on how many problems were piled up and how long necessary corrective actions were postponed. In most cases, there is a good chance to nip it in the bud or minimize its effect by monitoring obvious but critically important aspects of any project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clear-vision&quot;&gt;Clear vision&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first preventive action to diminish an onion’s stature is to have an explicit project goal and its relation to business strategy. Each project is unique and has its features. It lies at the intersection of the three interdependent targets: time, budget, and outcome, and aims to create a certain (in)tangible business value. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-01-31-project-value.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;55%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
As a rule, to start a project regardless of its basic parameters (size, &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complexity&lt;/a&gt;, business area specifics), primary focus (internal or external), and the expected outcome (a product, a service, or a result) it is necessary to have unambiguity among these aspects and a mutual general vision on targets, &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Five-steps/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;processes&lt;/a&gt;, opportunities, and constraints, shared by involved parties. Clarity on the project’s value is a starting point and an ultimate pre-requisite for your successful project journey, which follows by creating a project statement, definition of objectives, and elaboration of a project plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;defined-scope-and-objectives&quot;&gt;Defined scope and objectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fuzzy project objectives can grow a large onion and stimulate a waste of resources and efforts. To avoid it, objectives and project success criteria have to be defined and affirmed. Often project objectives are set based on the S.M.A.R.T. principle, i.e. there are to be specific, measurable, achievable, relevant, and time-bound. They are tightly linked to a project’s scope and influence its filling and defining what is included in the project and what is not. A negligent scope is a good manure for onion, which creates a risk of missing some or all project targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-01-31-project-scope.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A well-defined scope means that it includes all the work required, and only the work required, to complete the project successfully and meet the acceptance criteria. It is measured against the project management plan. The total scope of work to accomplish the project objectives and create the required deliverables is to be hierarchically decomposed into small parts for which cost and duration are estimated and managed. That structuring usually helps to straighten your path to project success and carefully audit the constraints’ landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accounted-constraints&quot;&gt;Accounted constraints&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each company has its own vision, strategy, and business targets that predefined directions of project objectives and outcomes. Internal and external business environments limit the options available to a company during a project, which have to be managed under certain circumstances and constraints. Focusing on results and positive thinking considering no limitations cultivates onion and assassinates the success of a project. Project constraints can be clustered into six categories: time-related, cost or budget-related, quality-related, scope-related, resources-related, and risk-related. Depending on the project, these groups can have different priorities, however, all of them should be accounted for and tracked. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-01-31-project-constraints.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
A change in one constraint often impacts the others. 
The most sensitive to any variation and vital for a project’s success is a triangle: time—cost—quality. Substantial or uncontrolled changes in it might be a sign of the “onion syndrome” in a project. The larger the bulb, the more difficult it is to balance and manage this triple, the other constraints are or will be also strongly affected, and project success becomes hardly achievable. Awareness of possible limitations allows for analyzing, monitoring, and controlling them, and making informed decisions during a project to take the required corrective actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reliable-planning&quot;&gt;Reliable planning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning is a must-have step in any project regardless of its type, selected methodology, and life cycle. It aggregates, clarifies and structures data, sequences, estimates and plans activities to fulfill the prescribed project work. The outcome of the planning step is a project plan, which shapes the desired path to project success and furnishes the basis for tracking and controlling constraints and their deviations. Although usually the initial project plan is modified over time to reflect changes in external and internal environments, it is important to take planning seriously and perform it with accuracy and rational detailing. Reliable project planning reduces uncertainty, anchors the optimal track to project success, makes project work manageable, alarms gaps and contradictions, and provides a solid ground to notice at an early stage an appearance of the “onion syndrome” as well as advantages to shut its effects on the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;committed-stakeholders&quot;&gt;Committed stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the managed project objectives should be &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholder&lt;/a&gt; satisfaction. People, groups, or organizations that could impact or be impacted, or perceive themselves to be affected by the project, are called stakeholders. They are to be identified, analyzed, prioritized and monitored, and the right strategies for their engagement during different project phases have to be developed in order to keep stakeholders satisfied and committed. Often, stakeholder satisfaction is a cornerstone of project success or failure. The key to stakeholder engagement is the focus on continual communication to understand their needs and expectations, in-time address issues, manage conflicting interests, and foster appropriate involvement in decisions and activities. Effective and efficient stakeholder communication ensures that the right message with the right content is delivered to the right person through the right channel at the right time. Once stakeholder satisfaction or commitment is missing, the path of the project can take a bulb, curve, spiral, or another fancy shape, but not the desired straight one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;skilled-and-motivated-team&quot;&gt;Skilled and motivated team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project team belongs to the key stakeholder group with the biggest impact on project success. Therefore, it is vital that a project team possesses the needed competencies and skills to fulfill work and tasks during different project phases and under a project plan to achieve the set targets and objectives. Lack of qualification of executors is one of the common causes of project incompletion, inferior quality of results, or significant increase in budget, time, and efforts spent on the project. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2023/2023-01-31-skills-motivation-matrix.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
Inaction or implicit faith in the outstanding ability of a project team to settle everything usually makes the situation worse. In order to close skills and competency gaps, requires their identification and then upskilling of team members or hiring the required competence on the market.
Besides skills, another essential aspect is motivation. Only motivated team members can be successfully engaged in a project and will do their best to achieve the desired results in an efficient and thoughtful manner. Once motivation is missing, it immediately affects the team’s commitment and the project path significantly deviates from the planned one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flexing-through-the-project&quot;&gt;Flexing through the project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing a project incorporates dealing with variations: stakeholders’ attitudes and commitments are mutable and transform over project phases; internal or external business landscape can curve in another direction and strengthen some constraints; minor and big mistakes in planning and estimating show up and many others expected, foreseeable, and unpredictable changes might occur. It is worth setting up reliable systems and processes that allow for identification, analysis, (re)planning, monitoring, controlling, and reacting to variable deviations and changes during the project, and keep focusing on the project’s vision while implementing adjustments. A pronged approach to execution in a combination with system thinking and timely decision-making support conscious flexibility targeted to project success and smoothing out the project path to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of projects is that they are dynamic, changing over time, and reflecting internal and external surroundings. At the same time, they require clear objectives, organization, structure, and processes, profound planning, monitoring and control, committed stakeholders and qualified executors to make targets real. There are a lot of traps and hindrances, including the “onion syndrome” in projects on the way to their success. However, learning, understanding, and practicing in project management aid to overcome obstacles and achieve outstanding results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@svetlana-ilina/the-onion-syndrome-in-projects-7-practical-tips-to-nip-it-in-the-bud-1c5e08d2007d&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="stakeholder" /><category term="processes" /><category term="project-management" /><category term="execution" /><category term="onion-syndrome" /><category term="vision" /><category term="constraints" /><category term="motivation" /><category term="competency" /><category term="commitment" /><category term="team" /><summary type="html">“The art of life is a constant readjustment to our surroundings.” Okakura Kakuzo</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">5 Steps to Make a Successful Project</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Five-steps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 Steps to Make a Successful Project" /><published>2022-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Five-steps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Five-steps/">&lt;p&gt;Professional project handling is a vital success factor for companies. In a time of economic instability, demographic challenges, potent climate change and green agenda, enterprises face the need for internal transformations, exploring new ways of working, and offering novel products and services for their clients. To hit these targets, companies, including those that never dealt with project business before, are forced to dive into project management. Their programs and initiatives have to be managed in an excellent, innovative, and responsible way in order to meet customer expectations and secure a competitive market position. To reach the desired operational excellence in projects, which in most cases is a key to profit and business growth objectives, processes are the starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;start-early&quot;&gt;Start early&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial project stage usually starts during the sales phase. It is well-known for companies that operate in project business. Their project management and sales teams work together to come to an amicable agreement on bids and order releases for projects. This is a highly desirable collaboration because the involvement of a project manager at a very early phase allows them to identify and report any potential risks before a contract is signed. A proper project handover is another cornerstone for a smooth project start. It might save a lot of time and money during the project phases. However, it is not rare that a contract is signed and a project suddenly appears in a backlog of a responsible department with no handover or briefing from the sales team. In an extreme case, a project can start without a project team or even an appointed project manager. This is a daunting situation and an enormous challenge to put such a project on track to meet the requirements set in the contract.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-12-04-pm-phases.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;150%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clarify-the-picture&quot;&gt;Clarify the picture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For internal projects where solutions and services are provided by an organizational unit within a company and project outcomes are to be used internally, the initial stage opens with the clarification of a business case with a scope, time frame, budget, high-level risks, resources, and requirements. Besides these critical aspects, it is also required to set clear project goals and objectives, define acceptance criteria for deliverables, and identify &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholders&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plan-ahead&quot;&gt;Plan ahead&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not matter whether a predictive, adaptive, or hybrid approach better suits a project, planning is a core pillar for its success. Project planning reduces uncertainty, alarms at an early stage of a possible scope creep, and provides a reliable ground to avoid an &lt;a href=&quot;/si/en/Onion-syndrome/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“onion syndrome”&lt;/a&gt; in projects. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/onion-syndrome.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
The first planning activities are started during an initial project kick-off meeting and followed by an in-depth clarification of the required amount of work; elaboration of a work breakdown structure; definition of a project organization in terms of roles and functions required to fulfill a project’s tasks; reliable estimation of project phases’ durations, costs, resources, and associated risks. It is necessary to define the duration and dependencies of project works, sequence them, identify critical items, a delay of which can collapse the entire project schedule, and plan time reserves. Other important aspects of a project planning are related to stakeholder engagement actions, project communication, and risk management. The mastery of project planning assumes a healthy balance between detailing and generalization: precise and accurate for decisive aspects and shortened or simplified for those that pose a smaller risk and &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complexity&lt;/a&gt; for a project. The outcome of this phase is a thoughtful project plan—a solid base for achieving the desired project results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;keep-on-track&quot;&gt;Keep on track&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implementation is the longest and often the most dynamic phase of a project. It entails the examination of the viability of different aspects of planning against reality and multiple revisiting of the previous phase for tuning a workable project plan. Besides consistent supervision of work progress, it is crucial to identify any deviations from a project timeline or objectives as early as possible to design, evaluate, and implement corrective actions. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/models/Boehm-cost-of-change.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
As a rule, the costs of postponed changes are increased exponentially over time. To avoid this situation, a project manager has to drive necessary changes, take in-time decisions, permanently audit the stakeholder landscape, maintain internal and external project communication, and trace risks. Focusing on essential items and rational monitoring of others usually yield a successful project completion and acceptance of its results by clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tighten-loose-ends&quot;&gt;Tighten loose ends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last but not least phase is a project closure. During this phase, all open points should be worked off; project results, the way of its execution, and lessons learned are to be discussed. The desired output of this phase is ideas of how and what can be made better in the next project, and what processes’ improvements can be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A well-thought-out setup of processes with a standing focus on continuous improvement is the prerequisite for getting stable results. It targets delivering excellent performance to customers, lowering risks, and maximizing outcomes. In project management, processes are the starting point and one of the core elements, but they are not a magic pill that guarantees the achievement of outstanding project results. The art of project management incorporates, but goes far beyond processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/5-steps-make-successful-project-svetlana-ilina&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="success-factor" /><category term="processes" /><category term="project-management" /><category term="planning" /><category term="execution" /><category term="onion-syndrome" /><category term="close-out" /><summary type="html">Professional project handling is a vital success factor for companies. In a time of economic instability, demographic challenges, potent climate change and green agenda, enterprises face the need for internal transformations, exploring new ways of working, and offering novel products and services for their clients. To hit these targets, companies, including those that never dealt with project business before, are forced to dive into project management. Their programs and initiatives have to be managed in an excellent, innovative, and responsible way in order to meet customer expectations and secure a competitive market position. To reach the desired operational excellence in projects, which in most cases is a key to profit and business growth objectives, processes are the starting point.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">How to cultivate a “difficult” client</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/difficult-client/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to cultivate a “difficult” client" /><published>2022-11-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/difficult-client</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/difficult-client/">&lt;p&gt;In any work environment, the customer is one of the key factors to set a pivotal way of business development. Sales theory has a long history of tiptoeing around customer needs, customer satisfaction, building trustful relationships, winning customer favor, and resolving problems to ensure an amazing customer experience. In the end, every client wants a product or service that solves their problem, is worth their money and is delivered with outstanding customer service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a service business, besides operational day-to-day activities, unique time-boxed entities aimed to deliver a product/ a service/ a result according to some peculiar customer requirements can be allocated. Each temporary entity is a small project. It has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/project-complexity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complexity&lt;/a&gt; and settles on the intersection of the interdependent targets: time, budget, and outputs, and possesses a risk of not achieving some or all of these targets. On the customer side usually exist several involved and affected groups with specific clout. These are &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.no-problem.cc/si/en/Stakeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;stakeholders&lt;/a&gt; who can support or block a project and its progress. Often they can be clustered into the categories: decision makers, subject matter experts, and users.
&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-11-11-stakeholder-groups.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;float:center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a small project, there is no need to use overly complicated instruments to ensure comprehensive identification, analysis, and fuhrer intentional engagement of stakeholders. However, proper stakeholder management without skipping any stages is vital for any project. It helps reduce a project’s complexity by aligning stakeholder expectations on the project’s goals, scope, and deliverables, recognize concealed political games on the customer side that might affect the scope or slay the project. Stakeholder management is a dynamic process that tracks changes in roles, interests, and commitment of involved groups through all project phases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fairness of these statements I’ve learned once again in practice. Recently, a company invited me to take part in their small project with a “very demanding” client. The company is a recognized provider in the talent management market. It has and promotes its own methodology embedded into high-quality products. It was a project with a new client and was supposed to be a door opener for future business. The client is a vast enterprise with a specific corporate culture and established structures, processes, and practices. The project sponsor—one of the new top managers on the client’s side—was familiar with the provider’s products earlier and invited it for the project. The main idea of the project was to replace the existing outdated product on the customer side with a new, deeply customized one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The provider offers different business services and has to deal a lot with product design, customization, and tailoring activities that require handling of basics of project management. The project manager did a good job. The scheduling was brilliant: logical sequencing, workable deadlines, clear milestones, and planned time reserves. An overview of the existing client’s product had enough details to get a complete picture. The features that must be in a new product were defined. The key stakeholders were known. The project team comprised professionals with a dozen years of relevant experience and possessing the expertise for such projects. A progress tracking system was in place. Each member got a piece of work and the execution began. Everything was fine until the first deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, it popped up that the project team and the client had different views on the final product. Even worse, each key stakeholder had her own vision of the product and they provided sometimes opposite comments and suggestions on improvements. Some stakeholders were not aware of or did not realize that the switch to the provider’s methodology would require a change in some working habits. Stakeholders from the users’ group blocked changes in processes. Stakeholders from the experts’ group trusted their own methodology more than the provider’s one. The familiarization of the customer’s experts with the provider’s methodology and users’ training in the new product were not included in the project scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/si/assets/images/2022/2022-11-11-credibility-matrix.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;65%&quot; style=&quot;float:right; padding:16px&quot; /&gt;
In most cases, the provider operates in or close to the “ideal” quadrant of the credibility matrix. The company has a solid portfolio of easy-going and demanding clients who acknowledge its expertise and trust in its professional advice. Here, the credibility of the new provider for the client’s experts was not high enough to rely on its expertise, so they requested changes to incorporate their old methodology but damaging the project’s essence. The different compromise attempts entailed a waste of effort through several rounds of reworking. A lot of reworking raised a question about the provider’s expertise in product design and produced an avalanche of new contradictory comments and feedback. The product had a good chance of not passing the quality gates. The company‘s focus drifted from the project margin to the reduction of losses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewed from an observer’s standpoint, it might be noticed that this situation is hardly unique and the hackneyed sales-slogan “one size does not fit all” is undeniably valid for stakeholder management. I am sure that everyone can recall a lot of cases when slipshod stakeholder management created an illusion of stakeholder commitment that subsequently multiplied the complexity of projects and generated problems out of the blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/how-cultivate-difficult-client-svetlana-ilina&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Svetlana ILINA</name><email>blog+si@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><category term="stakeholder" /><category term="case-study" /><category term="customer" /><category term="risk" /><category term="project-management" /><category term="execution" /><summary type="html">In any work environment, the customer is one of the key factors to set a pivotal way of business development. Sales theory has a long history of tiptoeing around customer needs, customer satisfaction, building trustful relationships, winning customer favor, and resolving problems to ensure an amazing customer experience. In the end, every client wants a product or service that solves their problem, is worth their money and is delivered with outstanding customer service.</summary></entry></feed>