<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2021-10-06T22:09:43+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Memory Leaks</title><subtitle>A mostly unordered collection of notes on electronics, embedded software, programmable logic, and everything else.</subtitle><author><name>Anton Kuzmin</name><email>blog+ak@no-problem.cc</email></author><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Arrow to Go Webinar: Building Applications on multi-core RISC-V based on Microchip PolarFire SoC FPGA</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/en/atg-webinar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arrow to Go Webinar: Building Applications on multi-core RISC-V based on Microchip PolarFire SoC FPGA" /><published>2021-10-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/en/atg-webinar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/en/atg-webinar/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ak/assets/images/2021/atg-webinar.png&quot; alt=&quot;Arrow-To-Go Webinar banner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparations are on the way to co-present on the first live-session of
the two-webinar series: “Building Applications on multi-core RISC-V
based on Microchip Technology Inc. PolarFire SoC-FPGA”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first session will take place on &lt;strong&gt;October, 13, from 9:00 to 10:30 CEST&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The webinar focuses on hardware related aspects of the development
process. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/martinkellermann/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Martin Kellermann&lt;/a&gt;
from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microchip.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Microchip&lt;/a&gt; will talk about PolarFire
FPGA and SoC-FPGA family architecture details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I will move forward with an overview of the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries-embedded.com/polarfire-soc-fpga-microsemi-m100pfs-som-mpfs025t-pcie-serdes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;M100PFS&lt;/a&gt;
module hardware architecture and interfaces available on an Evaluation
Platform. Detailed walk-through of the MSS configuration and FPGA
reference design will provide information necessary to adopt the
module to a custom design. A complete FPGA design flow will be
illustrated by integration of a small custom IP block into the
system. Hart Software Services (zero-stage bootloader) build and
programming of the resulting image (FPGA bitstream and e.NVM with the
bootloader) into the PolarFire-SoC FPGA device on the module will
conclude the presentation. Functionality of the IP core is briefly
exercised by accessing its registers from U-Boot command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IP core used for the illustration is an APB slave device capable
to generate interrupt request signal with a configurable frequency (or
a delay after the previous interrupt is acknowledged) and several
counters and latch registers. The core facilitates measurements of
various latencies in the interrupt handling process in an operating
system, and is a simple and useful tool to compare different executive
kernels and configurations on the real hardware with respect to their
interrupt response times. RTL code of the IP Core is available from
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ARIES-Embedded/interrupt_latency_timer.git&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second session is scheduled for &lt;strong&gt;November, 10th, 2021&lt;/strong&gt; and will
be presented by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/moritz-von-dawans-a285bb90/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moritz von Dawans&lt;/a&gt;.
He will illustrate the details of the software boot process, device
driver development and integration with a build system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The webinar series is organized by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/andreas-schwarztrauber-45246612/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Andreas Schwarztrauber&lt;/a&gt;
from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arrow.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Arrow Electronics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For details and registration
&lt;a href=&quot;https://register.gotowebinar.com/register/3461187153288908813&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Go To Webinar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anton Kuzmin</name><email>blog+ak@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Mi-V Virtual Summit Conference 2021</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/en/mi-v-announcement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mi-V Virtual Summit Conference 2021" /><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/en/mi-v-announcement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/en/mi-v-announcement/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://microchip.com/mi-vsummit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ak/assets/images/2021/miv-2021.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to make a presentation on behalf of ARIES
Embedded at the first Mi-V Virtual Summit Conference.  The
presentation will start at &lt;strong&gt;9:30 a.m. Pacific (18:30 CEST) on July, 21st,&lt;/strong&gt; and will be followed
by a live Q&amp;amp;A session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the conference you will be able to learn about many companies
participating in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microchip.com/en-us/products/fpgas-and-plds/fpga-design-resources/mi-v-partner-ecosystem&quot;&gt;Mi-V partner ecosystem&lt;/a&gt;
and their products built around RISC-V Instruction Set Architecture
and PolarFire FPGA and SoC-FPGA family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries-embedded.com/node/492&quot;&gt;ARIES Embdedded&lt;/a&gt;
will showcase
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries-embedded.com/polarfire-microchip-fpga-m100pf-som-mpf100t-pcie-serdes&quot;&gt;M100PF&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries-embedded.com/polarfire-soc-fpga-microsemi-m100pfs-som-mpfs025t-pcie-serdes&quot;&gt;M100PFS&lt;/a&gt;
modules based on Michrochip PolarFire family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;free-access-to-the-mi-v-virtual-summit-conference-content&quot;&gt;Free access to the Mi-V Virtual Summit Conference content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Summit page &lt;a href=&quot;https://microchip.com/mi-vsummit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://microchip.com/mi-vsummit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;if you registered to attend the event &lt;a href=&quot;https://mchp.us/3zGn8ZQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://mchp.us/3zGn8ZQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Anton Kuzmin</name><email>blog+ak@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="ru"><title type="html">Онлайн конференция и выставка Mi-V Summit 2021</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/ru/mi-v-announcement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Онлайн конференция и выставка Mi-V Summit 2021" /><published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/ru/mi-v-announcement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/ru/mi-v-announcement/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://microchip.com/mi-vsummit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ak/assets/images/2021/miv-2021.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;В июле этого года я буду представлять ARIES Embedded на онлайн
конференции, организованной Microchip для компаний-участников
партнёрской программы Mi-V. Выступление будет транслироваться &lt;strong&gt;21
июля в 19:30 MSK&lt;/strong&gt;, после выступления запланировано время для ответов на
вопросы.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;На выставке-конференции у посетителей будет возможность познакомиться
со многими компаниями, участвующими в
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microchip.com/en-us/products/fpgas-and-plds/fpga-design-resources/mi-v-partner-ecosystem&quot;&gt;партнёрской программе Mi-V&lt;/a&gt;,
и продуктами основанными на архитектуре системы команд RISC-V
и семействе ПЛИС и систем-на-кристалле PolarFire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries-embedded.com/node/492&quot;&gt;ARIES Embdedded&lt;/a&gt;
представляет на выставке модули, построенные на семействе PolarFire:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries-embedded.com/polarfire-microchip-fpga-m100pf-som-mpf100t-pcie-serdes&quot;&gt;M100PF&lt;/a&gt;
и
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries-embedded.com/polarfire-soc-fpga-microsemi-m100pfs-som-mpfs025t-pcie-serdes&quot;&gt;M100PFS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;бесплатный-доступ-к-записям-выступлений&quot;&gt;Бесплатный доступ к записям выступлений&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;страница конференции &lt;a href=&quot;https://microchip.com/mi-vsummit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://microchip.com/mi-vsummit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;если вы регистрировались до конференции &lt;a href=&quot;https://mchp.us/3zGn8ZQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://mchp.us/3zGn8ZQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Anton Kuzmin</name><email>blog+ak@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="ru" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">FOSDEM 2020</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/en/fosdem-20/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSDEM 2020" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/en/fosdem-20</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/en/fosdem-20/">&lt;p&gt;On the first weekend of February 2020, I visited Brussels to experience
an exciting atmosphere of a global gathering of free software
developers: &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/&quot;&gt;FOSDEM 2020&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides a unique opportunity to taste local beer and Belgian waffles
FOSDEM provides two days filled in with conversations with interesting
people, a possibility to learn what is going on in free and open
source software development and many areas next to it, and just a good
reason to break a day-to-day routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going there as a mere visitor would not have been for me a
sufficiently potent motivator to bother with all the arrangements and
expenses. To boost self-motivation I had submitted applications for
two talks in a hope one or the other would be accepted. Surprisingly,
both were approved, and that messed up almost all the plans for a
couple months in front of the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, those two days in Brussels left behind pleasant
reminiscence, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ak-fau/fosdem20&quot;&gt;presentations&lt;/a&gt;
saved on GitHub may be reused or just referenced to. Below are the
annotations of those presentations accompanied by a few comments
looking past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-hardware-debugging-of-ip-cores-with-free-tools&quot;&gt;On-hardware debugging of IP cores with free tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An approach to challenges of an on-FPGA debugging of IP cores based on
free software tools is demonstrated. Various aspects and related
problems of an on-hardware debugging are presented along with the
tools to address them, such as OpenOCD, sigrok/PulseView, GHDL.
Real-life working configuration and missing bits of software are
accompanied by the live debug session demo running on Open-source
Hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debugging of hardware blocks on an FPGA is always challenging and may
be frustrating, especially with no reliable tools at hands. Way too
often the process turns into developing and debugging of the tools,
instead of a target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commercial solutions are available (SignalTap, ChipScope, Synopsys
Identify RTL Debugger, Microsemi Smart Debug), at the same time there
are a lot of well-known problems associated with them: vendor lock,
single target, closed source and not always flexible enough, license
terms and costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to free software developers, essential tools for on-hardware
debugging of IP cores are available today. However, there are problems
associated with these tools too. The most notable ones are a weak
integration between separate tools and small bits of code and
configuration files missing here and there. A working combination of
tools among with explanations of how they may be used together to
debug IP cores is provided. A presentation covers such free software
as GHDL, sigrok/PulseView, and OpenOCD. Source code of free IP cores,
all configuration and script files and presentation slides are
available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A live demonstration of the PulseView connected to an in-FPGA logic
analyzer via JTAG interface with an open and low-cost hardware is
presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An outline of the open tasks and future development directions
concludes the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/schedule/event/fpga_hw_dbg/&quot;&gt;talk page&lt;/a&gt; on the FOSDEM archive site (with links to video recording)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/schedule/event/fpga_hw_dbg/attachments/slides/4171/export/events/attachments/fpga_hw_dbg/slides/4171/ip_debug_fosdem_2020_02_02.pdf&quot;&gt;slides (pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ak-fau/la-demo&quot;&gt;demo sources on github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;port-luajit-to-risc-vmotivation-first-steps-and-perspectives&quot;&gt;Port luajit to RISC-V&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Motivation, first steps and perspectives&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a need for a lightweight tools for experiments with RISC-V
custom extensions. Adding support for custom instructions in
binutils/gcc/llvm is out of range for many hardware architects. LuaJIT
includes a small and powerful assembler: dynasm, accessible from
within Lua interpreter. Currently dynasm supports following 32 and
64-bit instruction sets: x86, x64, ARM, PowerPC, and MIPS, and it is
just reasonable to extend this support to RISC-V.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lua itself is a very compact and simple yet powerful dynamic language,
its JIT compiler (luajit) makes it one of the fastest, if not the
fastest, interpreted language, and it is used in many projects, so
having it running on RISC-V would have use besides the mere internal
need for experimental platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-back-at-the-predictions-made-18-months-ago&quot;&gt;Looking back at the predictions made 18 months ago&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2020 there were no single language with JIT
support in the RISC-V foundation
&lt;a href=&quot;https://riscv.org/exchange/software/&quot;&gt;list of Available Software&lt;/a&gt;. I
was sufficiently bold in my talk to predict what languages were to be
first to provide it and, consequently, to shape &lt;strong&gt;J&lt;/strong&gt; RISC-V ISA
extension, reserved for such languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is entertaining to look at these predictions today. Slide 11
included this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;RISC-V J extension — what language will be the first to shape it?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Java&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;JavaScript&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;C#&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;what else?…&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what is available today in the RISC-V software list (in the
Non-C Compilers/Runtimes section):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Java — &lt;strong&gt;5 (!)&lt;/strong&gt; Virtual Machines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JavaScript: V8 and Node.js&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mono (C#)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forth — 3 different systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eclipse OMR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ada, Nim, Pascal, Go, Rust…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, was I right or wrong?.. Perhaps, both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I obviously underestimated interest in porting Java to RISC-V
architecture, but all the languages I expected to be available soon
are in the list now, along with many others I did not expect to see or
even have not heard about before. So, even if I was not exactly
accurate with this prediction, I see it as a very positive sign:
overall momentum behind RISC-V architecture is moving beyond cores and
gaining a traction in all sorts of software ported to the
architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only pity part for me is that luajit is not in the list, but the J
extension is not in sight either. An opportunity window is still ajar
and a tide of development in both RISC-V architecture and software
ecosystem around it is just at the very beginning with bigger waves to
be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links-1&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/schedule/event/riscv_luajit/&quot;&gt;talk page&lt;/a&gt; on the FOSDEM archive site (with links to video recording)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/schedule/event/riscv_luajit/attachments/slides/4170/export/events/attachments/riscv_luajit/slides/4170/luajit_riscv_fosdem_2020_02_01.pdf&quot;&gt;slides (pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Anton Kuzmin</name><email>blog+ak@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="en" /><summary type="html">On the first weekend of February 2020, I visited Brussels to experience an exciting atmosphere of a global gathering of free software developers: FOSDEM 2020.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="ru"><title type="html">FOSDEM 2020</title><link href="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/ru/fosdem-20/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FOSDEM 2020" /><published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/ru/fosdem-20</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.no-problem.cc/ak/ru/fosdem-20/">&lt;p&gt;Первые выходные февраля 2020 года я провёл в Брюсселе, где погрузился
в потрясающую атмосферу &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/&quot;&gt;FOSDEM 2020&lt;/a&gt; —
сборища разработчиков свободного программного обеспечения со всего мира.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Помимо возможности попробовать местное пиво и брюссельские вафли,
FOSDEM — это два дня общения и встреч с интересными людьми, возможность
узнать, что происходит в мире разработки свободного ПО и смежных
областях, и просто хороший повод вырваться из повседневной рутины.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Участие в качестве слушателя было бы для меня недостаточно сильным
поводом для поездки, так что я подал заявки на два выступления,
надеясь, что какая-нибудь одна будет принята. Неожиданно для меня, обе
заявки были одобрены, что заметно изменило все планы на пару месяцев
до поездки.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Тем не менее, два дня в Брюсселе оставили очень приятные воспоминания,
а подготовленные и сохранённые на GitHub’е
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ak-fau/fosdem20&quot;&gt;слайды выступлений&lt;/a&gt; всегда можно
использовать ещё раз или просто сослаться на них. Краткое содержание
выступлений и комментарии к ним год спустя приведены ниже.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;разработка-и-отладка-fpga-с-использованием-свободного-программного-обеспечения&quot;&gt;Разработка и отладка FPGA с использованием свободного программного обеспечения&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;В выступлении продемонстрирован подход к разработке и отладке
функциональных блоков (IP cores) на ПЛИС (FPGA) с использованием
свободного программного обеспечения. Отладка непосредственно на
аппаратуре и сопутствующие проблемы рассматриваются с разных сторон
вместе с программными инструментами для их решения, такими как OpenOCD,
sigrok/PulseView, GHDL. На плате разработки с открытой документацией
(open hardware) представлен реальный работающий пример отладочной
конфигурации со всеми необходимыми фрагментами программного
обеспечения.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Отладка функциональных блоков на ПЛИС всегда является сложной задачей
и часто может вызывать разочарование, особенно если доступные
инструменты ненадёжны. Слишком часто процесс превращается в разработку
и отладку инструментов вместо основного блока.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Для этих задачи доступны коммерческие решения (SignalTap, ChipScope,
Synopsys Identify RTL Debugger, MicroSemi Smart Debug), но с ними
связано много хорошо известных проблем: привязка к поставщику, работа
с единственной платформой, не всегда достаточно гибкое программное
обеспечение с закрытым исходным кодом, лицензионные условия и
стоимость лицензий.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Благодаря программистам, разрабатывающим свободное программное
обеспечение, сегодня доступны все ключевые инструменты для отладки
функциональных блоков на аппаратуре. Однако и эти инструменты не
лишены проблем. Среди самых заметных из них слабая интеграция между
отдельными инструментами и множество недостающих фрагментов связующего
кода и настроек. В выступлении представлена работающая комбинация
инструментов, и объясняется, как они могут совместно использоваться для
отладки.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Исходный код функциональных блоков, использованных в демонстрационном
примере, файлы настройки и слайды выступления доступны на GitHub.
Демонстрационный пример объединяет блок логического анализатора внутри
ПЛИС, который через интерфейс JTAG обменивается данными с sigrok PulseView.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Выступление завершается обзором нерешённых задач и возможных
направлений разработки.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ссылки&quot;&gt;Ссылки&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/schedule/event/fpga_hw_dbg/&quot;&gt;страница&lt;/a&gt;
на архивном сайте FOSDEM’а с видео выступления&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/schedule/event/fpga_hw_dbg/attachments/slides/4171/export/events/attachments/fpga_hw_dbg/slides/4171/ip_debug_fosdem_2020_02_02.pdf&quot;&gt;слайды (pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ak-fau/la-demo&quot;&gt;исходный код (VHDL, Tcl, C)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;перенос-luajit-на-архитектуру-risc-v-мотивация-первые-шаги-и-перспективы&quot;&gt;Перенос luajit на архитектуру RISC-V. &lt;em&gt;Мотивация, первые шаги и перспективы&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Для экспериментов с расширениями набора команд RISC-V желательно иметь
простые и компактные программные средства. Добавление поддержки
нестандартных команд процессора к binutils/gcc/llvm находится за
пределом возможностей многих разработчиков архитектуры. LuaJIT
включает небольшой и гибкий ассемблер: dynaasm, доступный
непосредственно из интерпретатора Lua. В настоящее время dynasm
поддерживает несколько 64-х и 32-битых архитектур: x86, x64, ARM,
PowerPC и MIPS. Поэтому представляется логичным добавить поддержку
архитектуры RISC-V.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lua является очень компактным, простым и мощным динамическим языком, а
реализация компилятора времени выполнения (luajit, just in time, JIT)
делает Lua одним из самых быстрых, если не самым быстрым,
интерпретируемым языком, и используется во многих программных
системах. Таким образом, перенос luajit на архитектуру RISC-V может
быть полезен и помимо удовлетворения внутренних потребностей в
экспериментальной платформе.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;предсказания--взгляд-18-месяцев-спустя&quot;&gt;Предсказания – взгляд 18 месяцев спустя&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;В начале 2020-го года в
&lt;a href=&quot;https://riscv.org/exchange/software/&quot;&gt;списке доступного программного обеспечения&lt;/a&gt;
на сайте фонда RISC-V не было ни одного языка с поддержкой
JIT-компиляции. В своём выступлении я набрался смелости предсказать,
какие языки первыми реализуют её и тем самым повлияют на J-расширение
набора команд RISC-V, отведённое для поддержки JIT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Интересно посмотреть на эти предсказания сегодня. Слайд 11 содержал
такой список:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;RISC-V J extension — what language will be the first to shape it?&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Java&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;JavaScript&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;C#&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;what else?…&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Посмотрим, что доступно сегодня на странице программного обеспечения
фонда RISC-V (в разделе языков и сред исполнения, кроме C)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Java — &lt;strong&gt;5 (!)&lt;/strong&gt; реализаций виртуальной машины&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JavaScript: V8 и Node.js&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mono (C#)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forth — 3 различные системы&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eclipse OMR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ada, Nim, Pascal, Go, Rust…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Итак, был ли я прав или нет?.. Вероятно, и так, и так.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Я явно недооценил интерес к переносу Java на архитектуру RISC-V, но
все языки, которые я ожидал увидеть в ближайшее время, сейчас уже
доступны, как и многие другие, которыx я не ожидал, или даже о которых
до этого ничего не слышал. Хотя я и не был совсем уж точен в
предсказаниях, мне это кажется очень хорошим признаком: общий импульс
развития архитектуры RISC-V вышел за пределы разработки
процессорных ядер, и набирают обороты усилия по переносу
разнообразного программного обеспечения.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Единственной ложкой дёгтя для меня является то, что luajit всё ещё не
в списке доступных программ, однако и про J-расширение пока нет
никаких новостей.  Возможность повлиять на формирование этого
расширения пока остаётся, а вал разработок, связанных с архитектурой
RISC-V и программным обеспечением вокруг неё, только поднимается, так
что можно ожидать больше интересных новостей и событий.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ссылки-1&quot;&gt;Ссылки&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/schedule/event/riscv_luajit/&quot;&gt;страница&lt;/a&gt;
на архивном сайте FOSDEM’а с видео выступления&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.fosdem.org/2020/schedule/event/riscv_luajit/attachments/slides/4170/export/events/attachments/riscv_luajit/slides/4170/luajit_riscv_fosdem_2020_02_01.pdf&quot;&gt;слайды (pdf)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Anton Kuzmin</name><email>blog+ak@no-problem.cc</email></author><category term="ru" /><summary type="html">Первые выходные февраля 2020 года я провёл в Брюсселе, где погрузился в потрясающую атмосферу FOSDEM 2020 — сборища разработчиков свободного программного обеспечения со всего мира.</summary></entry></feed>